<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>China and France, or, Two treatises the one, of the present state of China as to the government, customs, and manners of the inhabitants thereof ... from the observation of two Jesuites lately returned from that country, written and published by the French Kings cosmographer and now Englished : the other, containing the most remarkable  passages of the reign and life of the present French King, Lewis the Fourteenth, and of the valour of our English in his armies.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 112 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23787</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2163</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12191690</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12191690</idno>
            <idno type="VID">199150</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23787)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199150)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 101:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>China and France, or, Two treatises the one, of the present state of China as to the government, customs, and manners of the inhabitants thereof ... from the observation of two Jesuites lately returned from that country, written and published by the French Kings cosmographer and now Englished : the other, containing the most remarkable  passages of the reign and life of the present French King, Lewis the Fourteenth, and of the valour of our English in his armies.</title>
                  <author>Magalotti, Lorenzo, conte, 1637-1712. Viaggio del P. Giovanni Grueber tornando per terea da China in Europa. English.</author>
                  <author>Grueber, Johann, 1623-1680.</author>
                  <author>Orville, Albert, comte d', 1621-1662.</author>
                  <author>Thévenot, M. (Melchisédech), 1620?-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 220 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.N. for Samuel Lowndes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First treatise is an account compiled by Count Lorenzo Magalotti of the travels of Johann Grueber and Albert d'Orville.  It was translated into French by Melchisédech Thévenot, that translation subsequently being rendered into English.  Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Second treatise has special t.p. dated 1675.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715.</term>
               <term>Grueber, Johann, 1623-1680.</term>
               <term>Orville, Albert, --  comte d', 1621-1662.</term>
               <term>China --  Description and travel.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:199150:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:199150:1"/>
                  <p>CHINA AND FRANCE, OR <hi>Two Treatiſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The one, Of the preſent State of <hi>China,</hi> As to the Government, Cuſtoms, and Manners, of the Inhabitants thereof; never yet known to us before in <hi>Europe.</hi> From the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of two Jeſuites lately returned from that Countrey.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Written and Publiſhed by the</hi> French <hi>Kings Coſmographer, and now</hi> Engliſhed.</p>
                  <p>The other, Containing the moſt remarkable Paſſages of the Reign and Life of the preſent <hi>French</hi> King, <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth; and of the valour of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> in his Armies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. N.</hi> for <hi>Samuel Lowndes</hi> over againſt <hi>Exeter</hi>-houſe in the <hi>Strand.</hi> 1676.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb facs="tcp:199150:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199150:2"/>
                  <head>The preſent State of CHINA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the Thirtieth day of <hi>January,</hi> 1665. I went in the company of Mr. <hi>Carlos Daty,</hi> to viſit Father <hi>John Grueber</hi> at his arrival from <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> About two years ſince, he came out of <hi>China,</hi> where he had reſided full three years. He began his pilgrimage at <hi>Venice,</hi> where he took ſhipping for <hi>Smyrna;</hi> from thence, by Land, he marched to <hi>Ormus</hi> in five moneths; from thence to <hi>Macao</hi> in ſeven; ſo from the South Coaſt he travelled to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199150:3"/>North, through the large Empire o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>China,</hi> ſometimes upon Rivers an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> commodious Channels, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by Land, and at laſt he go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſafe to the City of <hi>Pekin.</hi> In his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from thence, he adventured t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> paſs, and ſurvey a Countrey whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was never yet ſeen before, by any i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Europe;</hi> namely, The unfruitful Sands of the Deſarts of <hi>Tartaria,</hi> which he paſſed over in three days, and came to the Coaſt of an Inland Sea called <hi>Kokonor,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Kokonor</hi> in <hi>Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tarty.</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies Great Sea.</note> not much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to the <hi>Caſpian.</hi> The River <hi>Jannus</hi> that runs through <hi>China</hi> with a ſtrange rapidity, &amp; diſcharges it ſelf into the Oriental Sea, near the Iſland of <hi>Carea,</hi> hath here its ſource. This River is the deep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt and largeſt of all that Countr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y Afterwards this adventurous Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller, loſt the ſight of the Sea to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter further into the Land, into the Province of <hi>Toktokai,</hi> which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:199150:3"/>barren and wild, that one of the Neighboring people can have any temptation to diſpoſſeſs the antient Inhabitants. Nothing is there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, but only ſome few diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed Tents of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> who lead a moſt miſerable life.</p>
                  <p>The beautiful River <hi>Toktokai,</hi> which is as large as <hi>Danubinus,</hi> but ſo ſhallow, that any Man, on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, may ford it over in the deepeſt place, watereth this bleſſed Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and gives unto it a name. From hence our Traveller paſſed through the Province of <hi>Tangut,</hi> which is very populous and belongs to the Kingdom of <hi>Barantola;</hi> he viſited, in his way, the City of <hi>Retink,</hi> and the Kingdom of <hi>Barantola,</hi> the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis</hi> is called <hi>Laſſa,</hi> and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King <hi>Teva.</hi> He is of a very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and noble Family of the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> of <hi>Tangut.</hi> His ordinary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence is at <hi>Butala,</hi> a lofty Caſtle built according to the <hi>European</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199150:4"/>mode upon a high Hill, having Buildings of four ſtories, of very good and regular workmanſhip. The Court of this Prince is numerous, and his attendants are extream laviſh in their apparel, which is, for the moſt part, of Cloath of Gold, and of embroidered Stuffs. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs this Nation is generally very ſluttiſh, and unhandſome in their attire: Neither Men nor Women wear lining next to their skin. Their common Bed is the ground, their ordinary food is raw Fleſh, and they are not ſo ſcrupulous to waſh their hands or faces; but they appear very kind and courteous to ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. Their Women have the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to walk about the Streets, as amongſt the other <hi>Tartars;</hi> but their other Cuſtoms are like to thoſe of <hi>China.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Their Arch-Prieſt or Mufty is called <hi>Lamacongiù,</hi> whom they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence as God, and believe to be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199150:4"/>related to their firſt King, but they name him the Brother of all the the Kings of the World. They are perſwaded that he riſeth from the dead as often as he dies, and that this Man hath already riſen ſeven times. The Kings and Polititians of that Countrey labor, by ſubtil means, to entertain the common people, in this ſtrange belief, and the <hi>Lamacongiu</hi> himſelf contributes to it; for he keeps his face always covered, and ſuffers none to look upon it, but ſuch as are acquainted with the myſtery. The Nobility do mightily reſpect him; ſome of them come to that point of adoration, as to covet that which is incredible, and to carry it about as a ſacred relick: From <hi>Barantola,</hi> Father <hi>Grueber</hi> tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled to the Kingdom of <hi>Nekpal,</hi> and in a moneths time paſſed through it. The two principal Towns are <hi>Catmandir</hi> and <hi>Patan,</hi> ſituate on the Banks of a River op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:199150:5"/>to one another. This latter is a young Prince very well accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed; he commands all the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdom as General. When Father <hi>Grueber</hi> was there, he was at the head of a great Army marching againſt a Neighboring King called <hi>Varcam,</hi> who made frequent inroads to ſpoil the Countrey. The Jeſuites gave this young Prince a Proſpective Glaſs, through which he cauſed him to look at a place where <hi>Varcam's</hi> Army lay encamped; he found it ſo nigh, that he gave order preſently to make ready and prepare for the fight, for he perceived not that this propinquity was but an effect of the Glaſs. This preſent was acceptable to him.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>Nekpal</hi> our Traveller went, in five days, to the Kingdom of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranga,</hi> where he could ſee no City, but only ſmall Houſes covered with Straw, and little Huts, one appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a Cuſtom-Houſse. The King
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199150:5"/>of <hi>Moranga</hi> pays a yearly tribute of 250000 Rixdollers, and ſeven Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants to the <hi>Mogol.</hi> From <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranga</hi> he travelled into that part of <hi>India</hi> which is beyond the River <hi>Ganges,</hi> and came to <hi>Minapor,</hi> the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of that Countrey; where he paſſed over that River, which is twice as big as the <hi>Danubius.</hi> From thence he went to <hi>Patan;</hi> and from that City, in five and twenty days, to <hi>Agra,</hi> the Royal City of that part of <hi>India,</hi> which is on this ſide <hi>Ganges.</hi> From thence to <hi>Laor</hi> in fourteen days. This City is built upon the Banks of the River <hi>Ravi,</hi> which is as large as <hi>Danubius,</hi> it runs into <hi>India,</hi> near <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ltaia.</hi> There he took Boat and was carried down the River, in forty days to <hi>Tata,</hi> the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt City of <hi>Indostan,</hi> the ordinary reſidence of the Viceroy of that Countrey; his name is <hi>Laskarkan,</hi> there he met with many <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Marchants.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:199150:6"/>
                  <p>From this place he ſailed to <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muz</hi> by Sea, from <hi>Ormuz</hi> he went to <hi>Perſia,</hi> afterwards he returned back to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> where he took ſhipping and arrived ſafe at <hi>Meſſina;</hi> from thence he went to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he received an expreſs command to go back again to <hi>China.</hi> For that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he travelled into <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Polonia,</hi> hoping to find another way through <hi>Muſcovia.</hi> By the Emperors procurement, he had got Paſports from the Dukes of <hi>Curland</hi> and <hi>Muſcovia.</hi> But when he was ſo far on his way as the Borders of <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covia,</hi> he underſtood that the King of <hi>Poland</hi> and the <hi>Tartars</hi> had made a conjuction of their Forces, with an intent to attempt upon the Duke of <hi>Muſcovia.</hi> By this means he was diverted in his paſſage to <hi>Muſco;</hi> for the fear of the dangers and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties in time of War, brought him back to <hi>Vienna,</hi> where he arrived at a convenient time when the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199150:6"/>was diſpatching an Ambaſſador, Count <hi>Leſhley</hi> by name, to <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople.</hi> The Jeſuite took this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to travel thither with a reſolution, from thence to go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in his intended journey: But when he came to <hi>Constantinople,</hi> he was mightily incommoded with a great rheume, with ſhortneſs of breath, and with violent pains in his ſtomach; ſo that being not able to proceed on in his journey, he went aboard a Ship bound for <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorne;</hi> from whence he was carried to <hi>Florence,</hi> where he remained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout eight days. In this time he was pretty well recovered of his diſtemper, ſo that he could go after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to <hi>Venice;</hi> from whence he paſſed through <hi>Friuli</hi> to <hi>Vienna,</hi> with an intent, by that way, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>Constantinople,</hi> that he might travel afterwards to <hi>China,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the orders of his General.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:199150:7"/>
                  <p>This Father is about forty five years of age, of a jovial temper, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary civil, as ſincere as a <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> his converſation is very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant; in a word, he hath ſo many good qualities, and is ſo gallant a Man, that though he were not a Jeſuite, all the World would eſteem and love him.</p>
                  <p>Monſieur <hi>Carlos Dati</hi> had ſeen him, the day before we had any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with him, in the With-draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Room of Prince <hi>Leopold,</hi> where he was entered into a converſation with him, which laſted not long; for the Father was called away and introduced into his Highneſſes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. After this firſt acquaintance, he intreated him to give him ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to ſome queſtions that he had a deſire to make him concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>China,</hi> which requeſt the Father granted in an obliging manner.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Mr. <hi>Dati</hi> deſired to know, whether the preſent King of <hi>China</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:199150:7"/>is the Son of the laſt Conqueror of that Kingdom? Where he kept his Court? Whether in <hi>China?</hi> or in <hi>Tartaria?</hi> The Father anſwered, that he was but his Grandchild; for the Grandfather being invited and brought in by the Rebellious Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuchs in the year 1646. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered all <hi>China,</hi> as Father <hi>Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> hath written at large in his Hiſtory of <hi>China.</hi> He told us, that the preſent King of that Countrey is about twelve or thirteen years of age; that he reſides at <hi>Pekin,</hi> the cheif City of the Kingdom, that his Father and Grandfather alſo did dwell there, according to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavels</hi> Rule; for he adviſeth a Prince when he intends to keep in his hands a Countrey newly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued to his Scepter, where the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants differ from him in Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, Cuſtoms, and Laws, to go and make there his abode. This is a Policy not ſo ſubtil, but that the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199150:8"/>
                     <hi>Tartarians</hi> have very well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and practiſed it.</p>
                  <p>We inquired next, what kind of <hi>Militia</hi> they had? And how the <hi>Chineſes</hi> were treated by their <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian</hi> Kings?</p>
                  <p>He told us, that the moſt part of the Soldiers of the Kingdom were <hi>Tartars,</hi> unleſs it be the Kings Guard which is a Body of about 40000 Men armed with Muskets and Bows of <hi>Corea</hi> or <hi>Japonia,</hi> for the moſt part. That the Inhabitants were not oppreſſed with Taxes, nor treated worſe then by their former Kings; for they have all kind of Liberty and Freedom of Religion. The antient Laws are yet maintained in force all over the Countrey, and Juſtice is adminiſtred by Judges that are natural <hi>Chineſes,</hi> only there is this alteration, a <hi>Tartarian</hi> muſt aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt in every Court with a limited Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which ſuffers him to alter no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the antient Cuſtoms and Laws of the Countrey.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:199150:8"/>
                  <p>We deſired him to tell us, what manner of Government they had under the King?</p>
                  <p>At <hi>Pekin,</hi> replied the Father, there are nine Judges or Courts of Judicature; and ſo it is in all other Cities of the Kingdom, where they are called by the ſame names, and hear the ſame cauſes.</p>
                  <p>The firſt and higheſt Court is called <hi>Li-pú,</hi> where half are <hi>Chineſes,</hi> and half are <hi>Tartars.</hi> It judges all Cauſes proceeding out of other Courts of the Kingdom, by way of Appeal, of what nature or buſineſs ſoever. The ſecond is named alſo <hi>Li-pù,</hi> but here the ſyllable <hi>Li</hi> is pronounced in a different manner from the firſt, for in the former it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>Reaſon;</hi> but in this latter word it imports <hi>Ceremony.</hi> This Court is the <hi>Forum Eccleſiaſticum</hi> that judges of all differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Learned; and decides all matters of controverſie in Religion.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199150:9"/>The third is ſtiled <hi>Pim-pù,</hi> which examines the affairs of the <hi>Militia.</hi> The fourth is for offenders, or the Criminal Court called <hi>Nim-pù.</hi> The fift is named <hi>Cho-pù,</hi> appointed for the Kings Treaſury, as the <hi>Exchequer</hi> is amongſt us. The ſixth is <hi>Cum-pù,</hi> which hath a care of all the Kings Buildings and publick Structures, and Edifices. The ſeventh is to ſee to the payment of all the Kings Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Attendants in his Family. The eighth hath an inſpection over the Kings Kitchin and Table. The Father had forgot the names of the two latter Courts, and of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes examined in the other.</p>
                  <p>In every City, theſe nine Courts are erected ſubordinate to one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; for example, that of one City, appointed for the <hi>Militia,</hi> is under the juriſdiction of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Court, which is in the cheif City of the Province; and from that, and all others, Men appeal
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:199150:9"/>to the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the Kingdom for the <hi>Militia,</hi> from whence they may appeal to the higheſt Court, which is the <hi>Li-pù,</hi> when it is a buſineſs of great importance.</p>
                  <p>From this Tribunal, there can be no appeal further, but to the Kings perſon, which is never granted without the puniſhment of one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred baſtinadoes, which every one muſt patiently endure before he can be admitted to the Kings preſence. The manner of giving them is very cruel; the poor wretch is forced to lye down upon the ground, upon his Belly, with his middle and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide naked, two men ſit one againſt another upon his Neck and Legs, with two great <hi>Indian</hi> Canes in their hands attempered before in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that they might be more pliable, then they ſtrike one after another; he that ſits at the Head, ſtrikes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Hips, and the other upon the Back, one after another ſo faſt,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:199150:10"/>that they are forced to ſtop ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and ſuffer the patient to breathe; for otherwiſe they would beat the breath out of his Body. The <hi>Mandarins,</hi> that is to ſay, the Noblemen of the Countrey, and the <hi>Tartars,</hi> do commonly inflict this kind of puniſhment upon their ſervants, for the leaſt offence. He that is forced to undergo this miſery before he can come into the Kings preſence, proceeds in this manner. He is to caſt in a ſtone at the Kings Chamber Window, then he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to come in; and if the King perceives that he ſuffers brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the firſt baſtinadoes in ſuch a manner, that declares his cauſe to be juſt, and the greatneſs of his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, he commands the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners to forbear, and the party to relate his buſineſs. If it appears then, that any injuſtice hath been done him, all that have had any hand in the judging of the matter
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:199150:10"/>before, are happy if they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, only for the loſs of their Offices; for commonly they are condemned to die.</p>
                  <p>I asked the Father, whether there were none left of the Race of the laſt Kings that reigned in <hi>China.</hi> For Monſieur <hi>Dati</hi> ſaid, that ſome affirm that a Son of the former King of <hi>China</hi> had eſcaped into an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent Iſland where he doth now live.</p>
                  <p>The Father aſſured us, that if we did but conſider where that Iſland was ſituate, that it was enough to convince us of the fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hood of that report: For it is in the Oriental part of <hi>China,</hi> therefore in ſuch a caſe the Prince was to paſs and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel many moneths through the whole Body of the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Army, and conquered Territories, for they were come that way into <hi>China;</hi> which is a thing not poſſible to be performed. The King his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199150:11"/>Father that reigned then, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come effeminate by his laſcivious behavior. He ſeldom ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf out of his Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce, more then once a year, leaving the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdom and Army, to 10000 treacherous Eunuchs that had called in the <hi>Tartars,</hi> who had ſubdued three whole Provinces, and beſieged the City of <hi>Pekin</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ound about, before the King knew any thing of their attempts upon his Government.</p>
                  <p>This ſudden approach and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, caſt him into ſuch a deſpair, that he reſolved to die. In order to it, he writ with his own blood upon a Buſquin of white Damask theſe words. <hi>God preſerve the new King, let him not trust my Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, but let him take compaſſion of my people.</hi> After this he hanged one of his Daughters, and then hanged himſelf under the door that leads into the Garden of his Pallace. The
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:199150:11"/>Queen alſo died in the ſame manner, but her Son and another of her Daughters were taken by the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars,</hi> and ſhut up in a priſon where they died alſo.</p>
                  <p>We inquired of what Family were the antient Kings of <hi>China?</hi> and the Kings that now reign, of what Houſe they are?</p>
                  <p>He informed us, that the antient Kings of <hi>China,</hi> were of the Family called <hi>Min,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>Light.</hi> Monſieur <hi>Dati</hi> replied, wherefore then doth Father <hi>Martinius</hi> in his Hiſtory call their Family <hi>Taimin? Tai</hi> anſwered Father <hi>Grueber,</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies Stock or Race; ſo that the meaning of <hi>Taimin</hi> is the Race of <hi>Min,</hi> as we ſay the Race, or the Houſe of <hi>Austria,</hi> or the Houſe of <hi>Arragon.</hi> But he told us, that the <hi>Tartars</hi> have no name to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, they are not diſtinguiſhable, but by their proper names. The Father of this preſent King was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199150:12"/>
                     <hi>Xun-chi,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>The Son of Heaven;</hi> and this Kings name is <hi>Tun-min, A great Light.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We deſired him to tell us, how the King lives with his Wives, and what diſtinction he did put between their Children, and the Children of his Concubins.</p>
                  <p>At this queſtion, he anſwered al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in the words of the <hi>Canticles,</hi> Chap. 6. <hi>Sexaginta ſunt Reginae &amp; octogint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>binae &amp; adoleſcentulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>est num<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rus.</hi> The truth is, the King hath fifteen Wives honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the title of Queen, they are not all equal, three of them are more eſteemed then the reſt? The firſt, and the cheif is named <hi>Cniſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>A perfect Queen.</hi> One of the others is ſtiled <hi>Tum-ſi, Queen of the East,</hi> and the other <hi>Si-fi, Queen of the Weſt.</hi> Theſe two Queens are named collateral, they attend upon the Soveraign Queen, but never ſpeak to her but upon their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:199150:12"/>knees; but the other twelve are never admitted to ſpeak to her: But if they deſire to ſignifie any thing to her, they do it by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of theſe Collateral Queens. The other Wives are more or leſs, according to the Kings pleaſure and humor; but it is certain, that there is never leſs then one hundred, they are all in the Guardianſhip of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuchs: But the Children of theſe Wives are all equal; he is looked upon to be the cheif, whom the King chuſeth as his Succeſſor. The King that reigns now, is the Son of a Concubine, he attained not to that honor for want of other Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, for he was preferred to five of his Brethren, Queens Sons, a little before his Father died; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, when the dying King had called them before him, he did not look upon them as able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in cheif, and manage ſo great an Empire. Therefore he ordered
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:199150:13"/>this Man to be ſeated in the Throne, and to be proclaimed King in his ſtead, and his Mother to be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Queen Regent, during his mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, appointing him four Tutors or Governors, of whom the cheif is named <hi>Samni.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I inquired afterwards, how they did bury their Kings?</p>
                  <p>He anſwered, that they did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bury their Corps, but burn them according to the <hi>Tartarian</hi> faſhion. The pile is not of Wood, but of Paper, it is almoſt incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, what a vaſt quantity is imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or rather waſted, in ſuch an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: For they do not only burn his Body, but alſo all his Wardrobe, his Moveables, his Treaſury, his Jewels; in a word, all that was uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the deceaſed, or that was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for his ſervice, the living Animals only excepted. Twelve Elephants bridled, and richly har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſed, loaden with <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Stones,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:199150:13"/>meral ds, Saphirs, and all manner of jewels of an ineſtimable price; three hundred Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes, and one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Camels carried the Kings Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure at the laſt Funeral. All this was unloaden, and put upon this Mount of Paper, erected to burn the Kings dead Body; when the fire had been put to it, the Gold and Silver did run from it in ſtreams, and force a way through the gazing multitude, who are not all idle lookers on; for ſome ſeek to advantage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the ſpoils of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed: But there is a great care taken to prevent ſuch kind of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences and ſtealth, by the watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Guards, and by the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous puniſhments inflicted upon ſuch offenders. The <hi>Tartars</hi> are very ſuperſtitious in this reſpect, and careful to conſume to aſhes the very Bones, and not ſuffer ſo much as the bigneſs of a Pins-head to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main; the Gold and the Silver that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:199150:14"/>is left, after the burning, is ſpent, to provide more Paper in ſuch a caſe, and to burn again the relicks of the dead Body, for the Souls ſake. At the laſt Funeral, when the expence of Paper was reckoned up, it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to no leſs then Seventy thouſand Crowns, and the whole Treaſure that was there conſumed, to Forty thouſand Millions. Three of the Kings domeſticks, a Privy Counſellor, a Chaplain, and a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubine, devoted themſelves to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon the deceaſed Princes Soul, and follow him into another life, by ſacrificing themſelves, aſſoon as the breath was out of his Body. They have always the liberty to chuſe what manner of death they like beſt, but commonly their Heads are cut off, which is the moſt uſual kind of death amongſt theſe people to puniſh offenders, only Soldiers are ſtrangled. Beſides theſe three Officers, many offer themſelves free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:199150:14"/>to death, ſome out of affection for their King, others out of a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious perſwaſion, unto which their Religion inclines them. But in caſe every one ſhould refuſe to die, and none would be willing to wait upon the Princes Soul, they force ſuch as he took moſt delight in, and his deareſt ſervants to depart and follow after him.</p>
                  <p>I inquired next, in what did the Kings Revenue cheifly conſiſt?</p>
                  <p>He informed us, that the Fields and Countrey did properly belong to the Peaſants, who out of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of their Fruits, pay about the tenth part to the King, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other part to the <hi>Mandarins,</hi> that is to ſay, to the Gentlemen that dwell in the Caſtles; for they are the Lords of their adjacent Fields. This Revenue that belongs to the Crown, is very great; there is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other that proceeds from all the Cattle of the Kingdom, out of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:199150:15"/>which, a tribute is gathered: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, there are great Cuſtoms upon Cattons and Rice tranſported, and ſeveral Mines in the Province of <hi>Tunan,</hi> which ſignifies a <hi>Southerly Cloud.</hi> Theſe Mines yield plenty of Gold, Saphirs, Emeralds, and all manner of precious Stones, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich the Neighboring Kingdom of <hi>Pegu.</hi> There is alſo an unknown quantity of Silver brought out of theſe Cities, <hi>Quangh-ceu, Canton,</hi> and <hi>Nanquin,</hi> which are the cheif Mart Towns of all the Kingdom.</p>
                  <p>We asked him, if the King did often ſhew himſelf publickly in the City? And how many Inhabitants may be in <hi>Pekin?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He told us, that he was wont to cauſe the Soldiers of his Guard to be drawn up in Battalia, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe once every moneth, where he did commonly appear, to cauſe them to ſhoot at a mark in the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows belonging to the City, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199150:15"/>the Walls that incompaſs it; for it is ſurrounded three times about, the uttermoſt Wall is the loweſt, the two others are higher; the nearer they are to the middle of the Town. The Ditches are deep and full of Water; about the City there are many pleaſant Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows. In one of them a great Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Wood is erected, againſt which, the King appoints his Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to ſhoot either with Bow and Arrows, or with Powder and Shot; one is to hit the Hand, another the Head, a third the Breſt. If the Soldier miſſeth the firſt time, he hath liberty to try the ſecond, and the third; if he fails all three, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out touching his mark, he receives a great many baſtinadoes for his reward, and is disbanded as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of his Kings ſervice. In the whole City of <hi>Pekin,</hi> there cannot be leſs then a Million of Inhabitants, ſome ſay that there have been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199150:16"/>Nine millions: But that is not credible, for the City is not ſo extraordinary large, and their Buildings are but of one ſtory high.</p>
                  <p>We deſired to know, how they did cover their dwellings?</p>
                  <p>He informed us, that they did cover them with Tiles, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Houſes have no other covering The Tiles of the Kings Pallace are of various colours, of yellow and marble, very pleaſant and beautiful when they are looked upon at a diſtance: When the Sun ſhines up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, they appear as if they were all of Gold.</p>
                  <p>We inquired, what Religion the <hi>Chineſes</hi> did profeſs?</p>
                  <p>He anſwered, that they did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Idolatry, that they were all I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters in their hearts, worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeveral Idols in private. But i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> we conſider only their outward profeſſion, there are three differing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199150:16"/>Sects. The firſt is of the Learned, that profeſs to worſhip a ſuperior Being, named in their Language <hi>Sciax-ti.</hi> Theſe two words are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven upon Tables of Gold, hung up in their Temples; unto them they offer Sacrifice, by burning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them Paper gilded with Gold or Silver; together with ſome ſmall round Balls made with Storax and Frankincenſe. But although they make profeſſion of this Religion, which appears more plauſible then the reſt; it is only outwardly, that they might be diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Bonzi,</hi> a ſort of men come out of <hi>China</hi> into <hi>India,</hi> extreamly ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, exceeding all others in Idolatry, and fond Conceits; at firſt they were in ſome good repute amongſt the <hi>Chineſes;</hi> as it common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happens when any new Sect ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that is not known. The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which they publiſhed of the Tranſmigration of Souls, which is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:199150:17"/>not altogether like that of <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras,</hi> got them the peoples eſteem, and procured them the envy of the Learned: So that they, in time, oppoſed the progreſs of this new Sect, more out of diſpleaſure againſt it, then out of love for their antient Religion. Therefore they have ſo well publiſhed and eſtabliſhed the worſhip of their <hi>Sciax-ti,</hi> that the Religion of the <hi>Bonzi</hi> is out of faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and date, and hath loſt all its credit; and they themſelves are looked upon no better then cheats. Now all over <hi>China,</hi> there is no kind of people more exclaimed againſt and decided; nor is there any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion more ridiculous then that. A man of credit ſcorns to exchange a word with them in publick, or to be in their company, unleſs it be in ſuch occaſions as are not to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided; as in Funerals, publick Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, Proceſſions, where theſe Idolatrous Prieſts are mercenary,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:199150:17"/>and hired to attend. The Nobility cauſe them to go in Proceſſion in nuptial Solemnities, at the birth of their Children, and ſuch like times. Their Proceſſions are preceded by ſeveral Inſtruments of Muſick, and attended with Banners, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played Enſigns, which they carry about their Idols; whoſe praiſes they ſing in Songs and Hymns, and to whom they burn Paper and Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond Sect is the moſt nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, for it conſiſts of the Citizens, of the Nobility, of the People and Peaſants; in a word, of all manner of People. Theſe pay their Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the Souls of their Anceſtors, unto whom they Sacrifice continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in their Temples; and in their private Houſes, by burning Paper and Frankincenſe. All over the Countrey, this is the ordinary Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice which is offered to the good and evil ſpirits every morning, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:199150:18"/>they go out of their doors. The third Sect is that of the <hi>Bonzi,</hi> who are moſt abominably ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
                  <p>We inquired, what the <hi>Chineſes</hi> did believe of Mans eſtate after Death?</p>
                  <p>They believe, anſwered he, that we ſhall be all happy, that we ſhall be inriched with more wiſdom, and delighted with more pleaſure then in this life; but they proceed no further to particulariſe how theſe advantages ſhall happen to Men. The Soul they believe to be immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal: But replied Monſieur <hi>Dati,</hi> if they believe that all ſhall be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in another World, how comes it to paſs, that they are not thereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to indulge themſelves in all manner of Vices? Nothing hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, anſwered the Father, but the fear of preſent puniſhment. Yet they have ſome light perſwaſions of Hell, where the Souls of the wicked
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:199150:18"/>ſhall be tormented; but they have found a way to get them out of thoſe Tortures. You muſt know, that at <hi>Pekin,</hi> and in every conſiderable Town, there is a great Temple e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, unto which, above three hundred little Chappels belong; every Trade hath one appertaining to it, and not only the Trades, but alſo every order and rank of Men, from the Magiſtrate to the Beggar. Now their perſwaſion is, that the Spirit that is to vex the Soul of the wicked man, deceaſed, haunts the Chappel appropriated to that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, unto which he did belong: For example, a Theif or a Robber ſhall bring a ſmall gift to the Theifs Chappel, to ingratiate himſelf with, and appeaſe the diſpleaſure of that Spirit that puniſhes Theft and Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, that he might ſpare him when his Soul ſhall fall into his hands. The Spirit makes no uſe of the gift, as you may imagine, but the <hi>Bonzi</hi>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:199150:19"/>that keep the Chappel: So is it with the reſt. This is a politick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, very well contrived for two good purpoſes, by that means they free themſelves from the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome apprehenſions of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and they cauſe a pack of Knaves to ſubſiſt, who otherwiſe would trouble all the World with their begging.</p>
                  <p>We asked the Father, whether amongſt the <hi>Chineſes</hi> there were any Religious Orders of Men?</p>
                  <p>To this queſtion he anſwered: There are no other Orders of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Votaries, beſides the <hi>Bonzi,</hi> who are moſt wicked Varlets, and infamous for their unnatural love of Boys; they want not opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to commit this abomination, for they are intruſted with the tuition of the youth; they are as the Schoolmaſters of that Countrey. This ſin is too common amongſt the <hi>Tartars,</hi> as well as amongſt the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes.</hi>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:199150:19"/>Inſtead of abhorring it, they make publick Profeſſion of it, by erecting Academies for that infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous purpoſe. This Vice hath ſpred it ſelf farther into <hi>Perſia;</hi> they are ſo baſe as to receive Boys in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and their Fathers themſelves, are not aſhamed to give their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and appoint them a kind of Portion, as to their Daughters. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Tartars,</hi> there are alſo Religious Votaries not much unlike the <hi>Bonzi;</hi> they have the care of the Sacrifices, and are attired with Yellow or Red Garments, that fall down as low as their heels, with large ſleeves open. Some of them carry on their heads Paper Miters; but commonly their heads are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; they march with naked feet, and all their habit is much like that which our Painters give to the holy Apoſtles. This Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Order hath many Convents of the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Women, ſituated, for
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:199150:20"/>the moſt part, upon High Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, of an uneaſie acceſs. Out of theſe Monaſteries, they never go out, without the leave of their Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, and ſeldom, unleſs it be to beg, and then the oldeſt of them are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. All theſe Nuns make Vows of perpetual Chaſtity, Poverty, and Obedience; their heads are unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and their hair is cut round, cloſe to their ears; their garments are like to that of the <hi>Bonzi</hi> in ſhape; but they are of a red colour, that of the <hi>Bonzi</hi> is gray.</p>
                  <p>We inquired of the Sciences pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed amongſt the <hi>Chineſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They have, ſaid the Father, the Works of <hi>Conſucius,</hi> who is as much eſteemed amongſt them, as <hi>Aristotle</hi> is amongſt us. <hi>Confucius</hi> lived about Three thouſand years ago, he hath left them a <hi>Moral Philoſophy</hi> mingled with <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Natural Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy.</hi> I have ſeen one of his Poſterity reckoned to be the Threeſcore and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:199150:20"/>third Man of his Race: He is very rich, and honored with the title of a Prince; for the Kings of <hi>China</hi> have always had ſo great a reſpect for this Learned Man, that they have allowed that title of honor to his Grand-children. Beſides the Works of <hi>Confucius,</hi> they are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally inclined to the knowledges of Numbers; but their <hi>Geometry</hi> is very imperfect, for it teaches only the more ordinary and practical part: They are not in the leaſt acquainted with the Theory, nor with the moſt excellent part of <hi>Geometry,</hi> as the <hi>Optick.</hi> From hence we may judge how little they excel in <hi>Painting</hi> and <hi>Architecture.</hi> They are mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly addicted to <hi>Chyromancy, Metoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copia, Magick,</hi> and ſuch like Arts. And in Judiciary <hi>Astrology</hi> they eſteem themſelves ſuper-excellent.</p>
                  <p>We intreated him to tell us next, ſomething of their Language, and of their Writings.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:199150:21"/>
                  <p>For their Language, ſaid the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is very poor, for it hath not above Four hundred words. All the Nouns are undeclinable, and the Verbs are imployed only in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitive Mood. I anſwered him, Sir if you would but continue but eight days in this City, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that I could learn ſo well the Language, that I might be taken for a Natural <hi>Chineſe.</hi> The Father laught at my confident conceit, and returned me this reply. After ſuch a ſtudy of eight days, you might poſſibly call a Man a Hog, inſtead of honoring him with the title of <hi>Sir;</hi> for all the ſignifications of the <hi>China</hi> Language conſiſt in the varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the accent, in the difference of the tone, in the aſpirations, and other alterations of the Voice, which are almoſt innumerable.</p>
                  <p>For example, <hi>Cin</hi> pronounced ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, hath no ſignification. <hi>Ciunun</hi> pronounced by lengthning the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounciation
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:199150:21"/>of the <hi>u,</hi> and ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Voice, ſignifies <hi>Sir</hi> or <hi>Monſieur; Ciu</hi> pronounced in lengthning the <hi>u,</hi> and keeping the ſame tone, is a <hi>Hog; Ciu</hi> ſpoken ſwiftly, or rather ſhot in haſte out of the Mouth, ſignifies a <hi>Kitchin;</hi> and <hi>Ciu</hi> made uſe of in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a ſtrong Voice, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſheth at laſt, ſignifies the <hi>Foot of a Stool.</hi> By this example you may ſee how one word may have five differing ſignifications. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Tien,</hi> pronounced plainly, hath no meaning. If it be ſpoken ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo that it makes <hi>Ti-en,</hi> it will ſignifie <hi>Sweet.</hi> If the <hi>(i)</hi> is accent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thus <hi>Ti-en,</hi> it means <hi>Bread. Ti-en</hi> uttered ſpeedily, ſignifies the <hi>Foot of a Table,</hi> or of a <hi>Bed.</hi> Moſt part of the words in this Language are Monoſillables, and may be joyned together in a various manner. But this Art of Joyning the words, is very difficult, and not to be learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:199150:22"/>in an inſtant; but that which renders it more uneaſie to ſtrangers, is, That they have neither Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters for their Letters, nor Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet; for they write all their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions in Figures and Ciphers, that ſignifie every one of them two or three words, and many times whole Periods and Sentences; therefore they are forced to write the five ſignifications of the word <hi>Ciu,</hi> by five differing Ciphers, for want of Characters and Accents; whereas we might eaſily diſtinguiſh them by the ſeveral Accents, which we might place variouſly upon the ſame words. This is the Perfection of other Tongues, although the ſame word may have divers ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, we can eaſily diſtinguiſh that which is proper to it in that place of the diſcourſe, where we find it by the words that go before, and follow immediately after.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:199150:22"/>
                  <p>But to return to this wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d <hi>Ciu,</hi> beſides the different Characters to expreſs the five former ſignifications. Suppoſe I intend to write <hi>Good mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Sir,</hi> I muſt not make uſe of the Character that ſignifies <hi>good,</hi> nor that of <hi>Sir,</hi> but I muſt write an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Character different from all the former, which alone ſhall ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie all theſe three words <hi>Good mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Sir.</hi> Or ſuppoſe that I am to write <hi>Yes Sir,</hi> I muſt not uſe the Character of <hi>yes,</hi> nor that of <hi>Sir,</hi> but muſt imploy another which will ſignifie alone <hi>Yes Sir.</hi> By this you may eaſily judge what number of Characters are needful to write our Conceptions in this Language. Therefore it is more uneaſie to read it, then it is to write it; for when we intend to expreſs our mind in writing, it is only requiſit that we ſhould underſtand the ſingle Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of words; for when they are joyned together, we may eaſily
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:199150:23"/>underſtand their meaning. But this manner of writing is not eſteemed, and only in uſe amongſt the vulgar ſort of Men. But the Learned muſt be acquainted, not only with thoſe ſingle Characters and Ciphers, but many others of a larger ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Some reckon them to be about Seventy four thouſand; whoſoever knows any more then the reſt, is eſteemed the moſt Learned, becauſe he is moſt able to underſtand and read more Books.</p>
                  <p>From hence it is, that this Tongue is ſo difficult to be learned; for as they have no Letters, they have no Dictionary to teach the meaning of the words; ſo that there is no other way to learn them, but to hear them ſpoken, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſound and accent, and to imitate the Inhabitants by repeating them often, as the Parrots when they learn to ſpeak. The Jeſuites have cauſed a Catechiſm to be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:199150:23"/>Printed, and certain Dialogues; the one to teach the proper terms, that they might diſcourſe of the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our Faith, and make the <hi>Chineſes</hi> underſtand them; the other is for the words moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed in a familiar converſation: Nine thouſand Characters which are in that Book, are ſufficient for this purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>This account of the <hi>China</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage diſcouraged me, and took me off from my inconſiderate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of learning it in ſix days. When I feriouſly think upon it, I cannot conceive how mans life can be long enough, for any to attain to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect knowledge of ſo many Ciphers, to underſtand them, when they are placed together, and to remember their different ſhapes and ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. I have ſought out a familiar example, to make me conceive the poſſibility of maſtering the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſuch a ſtudy. I remember
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:199150:24"/>the Figures that are imployed in the Demonſtrations of <hi>Geometry,</hi> may ſerve very well for this purpoſe; for although theſe Figures be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled in Lines, Triangles, Squares, Circles, and many ſuch Figures which are made by the croſſing and meeting of the ſeveral Lines; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, at the firſt view, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not only that which is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, at laſt, by theſe differing Lines; but alſo many other Truths, which muſt of neceſſity appear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the Lines can be drawn by a great many former Figures that enter into my mind, though they appear no more in that Figure and Demonſtration which they finally compleat: For all thoſe Figures and Truths are ſuppoſed to have been ſufficiently demonſtrated. There is yet another difficulty in this example; the Figures of <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrical Demonſtrations,</hi> are to be looked upon variouſly, as a ſtrait
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:199150:24"/>Line is ſometimes the <hi>baſis</hi> of the Triangle, ſometimes the Diameter of a Circle, or part of an Oval, or as the right ſide of a Parabole, or as the <hi>Latus tranſverſum</hi> of another. This conſideration cauſed me to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, the more, Mans ingenuity, and to conceive a poſſibility of writing and underſtanding the Characters of the <hi>Chineſes;</hi> for our skilful <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meters</hi> who are well acquainted with all the Figures of <hi>Euclides</hi> and <hi>Archimedes, &amp;c.</hi> And that are able, of that Truth that is thereby proved, and to gather from thence a great many other conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences that are deduceable, ſeem to perform ſomething more difficult then the <hi>Chineſes,</hi> who are only to diſcover the meaning of certain Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures imprinted in their minds, by a long continuance and uſage; for it is poſſible in the whole courſe of our
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:199150:25"/>life to attain to a familiarity with them all.</p>
                  <p>The Father <hi>Grueber</hi> told us of their Marriages, that the <hi>Chineſes</hi> when they came to nineteen years of age, or thereabouts, commonly eſpouſe a Woman that is reckoned as their only and lawful Wife; they receive with her a Portion in Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, according to their Eſtates; but it is always in their power, to put her away by returning her Portion to her again. When a Father de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers his Daughter in Matrimony, he never expects to ſee her again, he ſhuts her up in a cloſe kind of Sedan. When he hath locked her in, he delivers the Key to the good Woman, by whoſe Mediation the Marriage is conſummated; for there are ſome who make it their Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Trade, to deal in ſuch kind of Wares. The Woman ſhe delivers the Key to none but to the married Man, who is not to open it, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:199150:25"/>free his Bride from her priſon, but when ſhe is brought into the Nupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Chamber. When the Virgins of the Nobility go abroad, they are carried in Litters by Horſes or Aſſes covered over with a Vail, the reſt march on foot with their faces alſo hid; all kind of Women appear in this manner in publick. He told us afterwards, that when any Man hath taken a Wife, he is at his liberty to entertain as many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines as he pleaſeth, of whom there are two ſorts, ſome free, others ſlaves: The free are deſcended of Gentlemen, or other Perſons well qualified, who to free themſelves from the burden of ſo many Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, which they have by their many Concubines, are ready to part with their Daughters upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for ſmall ſums of Money, which they never reſtore again to the Men, when they divorce or ſend them away. All the Children re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:199150:26"/>ſtill with the Father, unleſs he pleaſe to allow a yearly Penſion to them and their Mothers. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines that are ſlaves, are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Daughters of the meaner ſort of people, they part with them for the ſame reaſon as the Gentlemen do with theirs: They bring their Children to the Market-place of the City to ſell them; Daughters to ſerve as Concubines, and the Boys as Servants; but they commonly drowned all ſuch Children, Males and Females as are crooked or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhapen at their Birth, or when they are otherwiſe deformed. For fifteen crowns any man may chuſe the moſt beautiful Girls of the meaner ſort to be his Concubine; but their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is moſt miſerable, for they are forced to carry water, and to drudge about the loweſt offices of the family: When their Maſter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to enjoy them, they cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe him; for they were bought for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:199150:26"/>that purpoſe; and although they may be of as good Family as himſelf; if they are taken in Adultery, they commonly looſe their heads. The Catholick Prieſts make uſe of theſe meaner Concubines, to inſinuate the Myſteries of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> into the minds of the other Women, and to teach the Children of the Nobleſt Families. They have been by this means ſo ſucceſsful, that many of theſe Women are become Converts, but they do not think it convenient to baptize them, in regard of that obligation that lies upon them, to grant to their Maſters all the liberty that they deſire.</p>
                  <p>The Catholick Religion is there freely profeſſed all over the Empire, without let or hinderance. In every one of their Churches, a Copy of the Kings Mandate, by which he grants a free exerciſe of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is graven in a Stone, and hung up in an eminent place, in the view
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:199150:27"/>of the Congregation. <hi>Christians</hi> are very well eſteemed of in all the Provinces of <hi>China;</hi> and the <hi>Tartars</hi> as well as the <hi>Chineſes,</hi> have liberty to turn <hi>Christians,</hi> and imbrace the Catholick Faith. The Learned Men of the Countrey, are familiarly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with our <hi>Miſſionary Prieſts;</hi> the greateſt oppoſition that they meet with, is from the Idolatrous <hi>Bonzi.</hi> The Father told us, that he had left in <hi>China</hi> ſix and twenty Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, four at <hi>Pekin,</hi> ſix <hi>Jacobins,</hi> and two bare-footed <hi>Carmelites.</hi> Theſe <hi>Miſſionaries</hi> wear the ſame habit as the Learned of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, a long garment of white Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask that reaches to the ground. Father <hi>Adam Schall</hi> is one of the four <hi>Miſſionary Jeſuites</hi> in this City, he hath lived forty five years in <hi>China,</hi> and is very well eſteemed of the Prince and People.</p>
                  <p>We inquired what kind of Coyn
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:199150:27"/>or Money, and what Weights the <hi>Chineſes</hi> uſe?</p>
                  <p>He anſwered, That they had but one ſort of Coyn Printed, named <hi>Cuxa,</hi> of very baſe mettle, each of them is worth about a farthing; upon one ſide is the Kings name, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the other, the name of the Coyn. Three hundred peeces of this money make a <hi>Lexu,</hi> which is worth about a Crown; they divide the <hi>Lexu</hi> in ten <hi>Ziens,</hi> in eight <hi>Fueus,</hi> and every <hi>Fueu</hi> in ...... <hi>Cuxas.</hi> They uſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Money, both Gold and Silver pieces, which they cut off as they ſpend; for that purpoſe, they carry in their Boots, and about them, Seales and Cizers.</p>
                  <p>The Pound weight of <hi>China</hi> is ſixteen of our ounces. They mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by a cubit: All kind of Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als is very cheap, as well as their cloathing; for five <hi>Fucas,</hi> which are five of our pence, one may buy a very large Hen; by that any may
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:199150:28"/>judge of every thing elſe that is ſold, at a proportionable rate.</p>
                  <p>We asked him concerning their Meat and Drink.</p>
                  <p>He told us, that they had no Wine, although their Countrey af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords excellent Grapes. The <hi>Euro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peans</hi> ſometimes make Wine with them, which the Inhabitants like very well, but they dare not drink of it, but in private, for this proud Nation have a Law in force to puniſh ſeverely all ſuch as ſhall bring in new modes of living. Their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary drink is <hi>Thé,</hi> and Wine made of Rice; they extract it doubtleſs by the Limbick and the Still. It is not certainly known how they do it, for they will not diſcover the ſecret of any of their Arts to ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, unleſs they ſwear firſt to profeſs it, and it may coſt them their lives, if they fail afterwards. They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to drink hot liquors for that purpoſe; they are always upon the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:199150:28"/>fire in veſſels near their Tables. In Summer they caſt a little quantity of Ice in their drink, which they ſuffer to remain there only for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the liquor may receive from it, in ſo ſhort a time, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of its cold nature to cool the ſtomach; but they quickly take it out again, that they might not looſe the pleaſure of drinking it hot. They keep their Ice, as we do in <hi>Europe;</hi> it is ſold about the Towns very cheap, they uſe it more to cool their Fruits, then their Drinks, for they delight to eat them very cold.</p>
                  <p>But to return to their liquors, Wine made of Rice, appears of a whiteneſs, inclining a little to the Amber colour, and mixed with a Golden Yellow, very beautiful to the eye. It hath a very pleaſant taſte, and ſo delicious, that it ſeems as good as the beſt Sack. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people drink out of Earthen
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:199150:29"/>Veſſels, but the rich and noble are provided with Golden and Silver, adorned with ordinary Workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. The greateſt Lords uſe drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Veſſels made with the Horns of a <hi>Rhinocerot,</hi> imbelliſhed in a courſe manner, inriched with Gold, and ſometimes with Diamonds. For their Meats they have all kind of varieties, as we have in <hi>Europe,</hi> of Veniſon, and of Fowl, of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Fruits and Pulſe. Their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are better then ours, for they are nearer to the <hi>Molucas.</hi> Their Wheat is very good, they can make Meal of it, but they have no skill to knead it into Bread; therefore in lieu of that, they uſe Rice which hath ſoaked in the Water, and been parched and dried afterwards at the fire. This they take and carry to their Mouths, with long ſticks that ſerve them inſtead of Forks. In their left hands they are commonly provided with a Porringer full of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:199150:29"/>this Rice, which they uſe inſtead of Bread, taking it out with their ſticks at every bit of Meat. They have no skill, nor taſte to ſeaſon their Meats well: In the ſame Pot they boil Pork, Hare, Fiſh, Veal, and Pheaſant together; and their beſt Cooks are continually pouring in abundance of Water, while they are boiling. When they are ſodden, they fill their Porringers and Diſhes with this mad <hi>Oleo Podrido,</hi> which ſerves them inſtead of Pottage. The moſt ordinary Fleſh that they feed upon is Pork; their Mutton is in good eſteem amongſt them. The poorer ſort eat Aſſes, Dogs, Cats, and ſuch like things, which they buy in Shambles, appointed for all kind of Fleſh. The dried Legs of Dogs, well and curiouſly ſmoaked as we do our Neats Tongues, is a bit very ſavory to them; they commonly reſerve it for their deſſert and laſt morſel at dinner; they
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:199150:30"/>eſteem it a great fortifier of the ſtomach. They bring every kind of Meat ſeverally in diſtinct Diſhes, but they have but two ſorts of Saw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to encourage and provoke appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite. The firſt is a kind of Paſte made with ſmall Beans in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; they beat the Beans ſoaked in Water, and then ſtir them well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the Water; when upon the top there appears a thin cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or green skin, they ſtrain all through a Linnen cloath into clean Water; the fineſt ſubſtance runs through, but the skins remain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind. This they uſe inſtead of Sawce to all their Meats, and inſtead of Salt alſo; for they never ſalt them otherwiſe, although they want not Wells and Fountains of Salt and Brackiſh Water in all the Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern Provinces. The other Sawce is named <hi>Mi-ſſo,</hi> which is made of a rotten Grain that yields a moſt noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſmell; they do not boil it
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:199150:30"/>with the reſt of their Meats, but they put it by it ſelf in Sawcers; and when they are at dinner, they dip their morſels of Meat in this ſtrong and filthy Muſtard. At their Feaſts, and at the Tables of their Nobles and Lords, they garniſh their Diſhes variouſly, but ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily with Rice, Herbs, or with hard Eggs, minced ſmall and fried. When their Cooks have ſhewn all their art and skill in ſuch occaſions, it is no light puniſhment to condemn a Man of <hi>Europe,</hi> to carry thither an empty ſtomach: Therefore when ſtrangers are invited, they provide themſelves with a good dinner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, for they are certain to meet with nothing there fit for their appetites.</p>
                  <p>Their Tables ſtand round about the room where the Feaſt is to be held, never above two or three are together at the ſame Table, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is wont to ſit alone at the lower
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:199150:31"/>moſt. They uſe no Table-cloaths, but cover them with as many neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary utenſils, as there ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons at the Table: Theſe utenſils are a diſh to drinkin, a Plate of Rice, another of their dainty <hi>Mi-ſſo,</hi> and two of theſe Sticks, that ſerve them inſtead of Forks. All their Diſhes are of Porcelane, the Kings as well as the meaneſt Subjects, with this difference, That the one is of a finer ſubſtance then the other. When the invited gueſts are ſeated, an Officer uſhers in the firſt ſervice; and when all the Tables are furniſhed, he makes a ſign to all to begin to eat. If any ſhould offer to touch the Meat before he hath given the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, he would be ſeverely checked, and looked upon as a Clown or an impatient Glutton. The ſignal or liberty of eating, is given by ſaying to them all <hi>Zin,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite you;</hi> then the gueſts all anſwer, <hi>Zin, zin, zin,</hi> repeating this word
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:199150:31"/>three times, as the <hi>Italian</hi> Prieſts do the word <hi>Peace,</hi> when they ſalute and embrace one another. After this, they all carry their hands to their ſeveral Diſhes together, and the Meat to their Mouths; and if any do not eat at the ſame time, as the reſt, the Officer calls upon them; for they think that the perfection of their Feaſts conſiſts in eating altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, otherwiſe they judge it to be out of order, and unhandſome. When the Officer eſteems that they have ſufficiently eaten of the firſt ſervice, he cauſeth the ſecond to be brought in, and after that the third, obſerving the ſame ceremonies and decency, as at the firſt. Likewiſe, when he thinks it is time to drink, he invites them to it, in the ſame manner as he doth to eat; but they muſt all empty their Cups. When they begin to drink the firſt time, the Stage-players enter into the Room, ſome of them are common,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:199150:32"/>who play for Mony at every Houſe, when they are hired, others are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by Noblemen; the richeſt have ſeveral companies of them, as the great Lords in <hi>Europe</hi> have Muſicians. Theſe kind of people are very richly cloathed; when they come in, they addreſs themſelves to him that ſits at the higheſt Seat to ſhew him their Book of Comedies, and to deſire him to tell them upon what ſubject to play. He ſends them, out of civility, down to another, with their Book, which comes at laſt to the Maſter of the Houſe, who commonly tells them to act what Comedy they pleaſe. This Comedy laſts about a quarter of an hour: The Subjects of the moſt part of their Comedies, are taken from the Lives and Heroick Actions of their former Kings and Queens; when the Comedy is ended, the Officer enters in with other Diſhes of Meat; and when they are all taken away,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:199150:32"/>and have ended their drinking, the Comedians return again, obſerving the ſame ceremony as before, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat the aſſiſtants one after another, to appoint the ſubject, upon which they are to diſcourſe and act. When this ſecond Comedy is finiſhed, the Officer comes again to give his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance: Now this unpleaſant di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion laſts ſometimes ſix or ſeven hours. I had almoſt forgot, ſaid the Father, to tell you, that they have no <hi>Olives</hi> growing in <hi>China,</hi> therefore they make uſe of three other ſorts of Oyl: The richeſt have an Oyl taken out of the Berries of Flowers of that Countrey, that grow upon Bryars: This is very ſweet and pleaſant. I know not how they make it, but they have a great quantity of it; for their Land is as fruitful of ſuch Bryars, as ours is of Nettles. The meaner ſort of people make uſe of another Oyl, extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from a Grain which they call <hi>Tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelin;</hi>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:199150:33"/>it hath almoſt the ſame taſte as the Oyl of <hi>Seſamum,</hi> a little bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The Countrey People, as in <hi>Poland,</hi> employ the Oyl of <hi>Line</hi> or <hi>Flax,</hi> or another kind of Oyl ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from a Plant named <hi>Ma-ſen,</hi> which hath a moſt odious and ſtrong ſmell. They never eat any Sallads, nor other raw Herbs; many of their Fruits they preſerve in Salt and Vinegar. In ſhort they are not cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in their taſte and eating, but are filthy and unhandſome. When we had a Pheaſant, or a Hair, we could not abide to ſee our <hi>China</hi> Cook handle and dreſs it; we were forced to ſpit and dreſs it our ſelves, and eat it in the moſt retired Room, having firſt forbidden the door to be opened to any that ſhould come, unleſs it be to the Kings Officers. And that none might ſurpriſe us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares, while our Meat was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring, always one of us ſtood Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel at the Window, to give warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:199150:33"/>of any Mans coming up to us.</p>
                  <p>It is a very ſtrange thing ſaid Monſieur <hi>Dati,</hi> that this Nation that hath ſo many Sheep and Cows, have no skill to make Cheeſe with their Milk, in any other manner, but with ſmall Beans.</p>
                  <p>This proceeds, replied the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from their unſufferable Pride; for they ſcorn to learn any thing, from ſtrangers, eſpecially from the <hi>Tartars;</hi> becauſe the <hi>Tartars</hi> make Cheeſe that is enough to cauſe them to abominate ſuch a compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for that Nation. I could never make uſe of any of their Cheeſe, nor of the Milk of the <hi>Chineſes;</hi> for both yield a moſt odious ſmell. The <hi>Tartars</hi> make their Cheeſe of the ſhape of our Cracknels, and hang them up with ſtrings, a great many together, at their Shops, to invite the hungry ſtomach to buy them; they are ſo grievous hard, that the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:199150:34"/>Flint Stones are not more. They are not to be eaten, but after they have been ſoftned by the Fire, and molified as our Wax.</p>
                  <p>But the <hi>Chineſes,</hi> are far more nice and curious in their ſleeping, then in their eating and drinking. In Winter they ſpred Cotten Mats upon little Furnaces, and ſquare Stoves, named <hi>Caù,</hi> where they keep a very moderate Fire. Upon theſe Mats they lay very fine Sheets of Cotton, all their Linnen is of that ſubſtance; for they uſe their <hi>Line</hi> to make Oyl, and their <hi>Flax</hi> to twiſt into Ropes. At the four corners of their <hi>Caù,</hi> there are Pillars as at our Beds; at the top round, the Curtains are faſtned, which they call <hi>Cai-ïà.</hi> In Winter they are of Cloth, or of ſome other thick ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; but in Summer they are of a very fine and thin Cotton, to keep off the Musketas. When the cold is over, they carry their Mats, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:199150:34"/>lay them upon Boards or Tables; and in the heat of Summer, inſtead of Wool and Cotton, they fill them with a Sea weed, which when it is dried, is as ſoft as Silk, and as light as Feathers: It is naturally very cool. Their Bolſters and Pillows are very neatly made of the thinneſt and ſofteſt skins of Reed, which we call <hi>Indian Cane,</hi> in the manner of Hurdles. When the inſide is emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied out, and ſhut up cloſe, they are filled with wind, which yields in the hotteſt Seaſon much pleaſure. The head feels them to be very ſoft, and never ſinks deep; it is not buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as in our Down-pillows, they are very ſmooth. Their head are as though they were upon Springs, when they turn; and at the leaſt motion, they cauſe their Pillows and Bolſters, to ſend up a cold and freſh Air to cool their faces, which is a notable advantage in the hotteſt nights of the Summer.</p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:199150:35"/>
                  <p>Their Chairs are of the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the Back and the Elbows are made of the Skins of <hi>Indian Cane,</hi> very commodious to ſit down. The <hi>Tartars</hi> are not ſo effeminate to make uſe of all theſe things, they ſleep upon the bare ground as the <hi>Turks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We deſired him to tell us ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Kings pomp, and of the magnificence of his Throne, when he appears in publick in all his grandeur.</p>
                  <p>He aſſured us, that the former Kings of <hi>China</hi> did delight in a great deal of glory and ſtate; but that the preſent King of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> who reigns now in <hi>China,</hi> is not ſo cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious: He is content in his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſplendor, to ſit upon a Carpet ſpred on the ground.</p>
                  <p>Monſieur <hi>Dati</hi> deſired to know from the Father, in what the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes</hi> were moſt expenſive.</p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:199150:35"/>
                  <p>He anſwered, that they ſpent much in their Funerals, in the great quantity of Perfumes and Wax, which they did there burn, in the making of Wooden Statues, in their Frankincenſe, which they did offer to the deceaſed, and ſpecially in the rare Coffins, in which they put the dead Bodies. They are of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Wood, as of <hi>Aloes,</hi> of <hi>Yellow Saunders,</hi> or of ſome other <hi>Aroma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Wood</hi> of a great value: This ſerves inſtead of imbalming.</p>
                  <p>We inquired of the goodneſs of the Air, of the Countrey, and how long the Inhabitants do commonly live.</p>
                  <p>The Air, ſaid he, is very good every-where; therefore the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey people that are temperate in their diet, commonly live to be very old; ſome are one hundred years of age. The Nobility at forty ſeem to be old, and when they ſee fifty, they begin to be craſie; this
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:199150:36"/>difference proceeds from their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries with the Female Sex, and their immoderate eating, in which they preſcribe no bounds to themſelves. Their Daughters ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom come to be thirty years of age, becauſe their Mothers are wont to tie and bind their Legs aſſoon as they are born; for they think all their beauty conſiſts in crooked Legs, which is that part alone of their Bodies ſeen when they go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad.</p>
                  <p>This ſtrange and unnatural bending and tying of their Legs ſo young, diſorders the Channels, through which; the nouriſhment of their Members paſſeth, and ſtops the Conduits, in ſuch a manner, that neither their Legs nor their Bodies ever come to a perfect ſtature and bigneſs; for by that means, the Blood is hindered in its ordinary circulation; and the complexion and conſtitution of their Bodies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:199150:36"/>vitiated, it haſtens them the ſooner to their Graves.</p>
                  <p>We deſired him to tell us, which were their moſt noted Feſtivals?</p>
                  <p>He anſwered us, That they cheifly obſerve three; the one at the firſt New Moon in <hi>February,</hi> the ſecond in <hi>November,</hi> and the third at the Kings Birth-day. In every one of theſe Feſtivals, the King goes out of the City, attended upon by all the Nobility and Lords of the Court; by the Magiſtrates, Officers of the Law, and by the Learned Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Every one wears an habit ſuitable to his dignity and place. All their Garments are differing from one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, none but the King dares wear a Pearl alone at the top of his Gap. Many of the moſt eminent Lords have precious Stones, and ſome Pearls; but always a Ruby, an Emerald, or a Jaſper, is put with it; for none but the King is to wear it alone. He wears alſo as marks of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:199150:37"/>his Royalty, two Storks embroider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Silver upon his Breſt. The <hi>Mandarins</hi> have other Animals: There are nine cheif differences, by which the Nobility is diſtinguiſhed in their habits. The firſt hath a Crane for his Badge, the ſecond a Lion, the third an Eagle, the fourth a Peacock; I do not remember the reſt, nor what differences are to be noted in the Garments of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Learned Men. I only remember the Badge of the <hi>Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticians,</hi> they wear four little Squares of Jaſper, tied with ſilken ſtrings at their Girdles. In the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the Squares there is a Ruby, and upon the top of their Bonnet, they bear a Ruby and a Pearl to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. The moſt ordinary colours of their Garments, are Red, Blew, Orange mixed with Blew. We have already ſaid, that their <hi>Bonzi</hi> are cloathed in Gray, and the Learned in White.</p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:199150:37"/>
                  <p>I remember that at every Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val obſerved at the New Moon in <hi>February,</hi> every one is wont to melt or caſt ſome piece of Mettle; upon which they repreſent the Figure of a Creſcent or New Moon; and they call this Feſtival, <hi>The Sacrifice of the Hare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We inquired, Whether the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes</hi> had any Memorials ſo antient, that give an account of the paſſages of ſo many thouſand years ago, as ſome do affirm.</p>
                  <p>He told us, that they had no Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories more antient then King <hi>Tao,</hi> who lived about four thouſand ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hundred years ago; and that they had no Hiſtories of antienter date, that ſpeak of the beginning and continuance of the World.</p>
                  <p>We put the Father next upon the Art of Navigation, to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they believe in <hi>China,</hi> that there is any paſſage out of <hi>Aſia</hi> into <hi>America;</hi> he aſſured us, that they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:199150:38"/>had but little skill in Navigation; that they know not well how to make uſe of the <hi>Compaſs,</hi> or rather this knowledge is defective. Their greateſt Veſſels are not able to carry above fifty Men, their Sails are made of Mat, but ſo artificially, that they can go almoſt with any wind. Their rowing differs from ours, for they move their Oars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and behind. Therefore as they have no great inſight into the Art of Navigation, it is not poſſible that they ſhould be able to adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture far at Sea, they dare not looſe the ſight of the Land.</p>
                  <p>Concerning their paſſing from <hi>Aſia</hi> into <hi>America,</hi> the Father told us, That he knew nothing certain, becauſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the <hi>Holland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> have been diſappointed in their attempting to paſs through the <hi>Frozen Sea,</hi> where they have no manner of Trade: For the <hi>Tartars</hi> they are no great Traders, and it is
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:199150:38"/>not probable, that any of them will venture upon a meer curioſity, to open that paſſage. It is not likely, that the <hi>Chineſes</hi> will leave their Countrey, to undertake any ſuch hazardous voyage: Nevertheleſs, it is generally believed, that there is ſome-where a paſſage, or that <hi>Aſia</hi> is divided from <hi>America,</hi> but by a Narrow Sea. The continual ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of many wild Fowl of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica,</hi> in the Southern Parts of <hi>Tartaria,</hi> do very much ſtrengthen this opinion: For it is not probable, that they would there be ſeen, if <hi>America</hi> and <hi>Tartaria</hi> were not joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, or not far from one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
                  <p>We asked him concerning the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings, Plays, and Gardens of <hi>China.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Chineſes,</hi> replied the Father, never dance, but the <hi>Tartars</hi> uſe that ſport amongſt themſelves; the Men with the Men, and the Women with the Women; but never both Sexes
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:199150:39"/>together. Their Muſick conſiſts in ſtriking their hands one againſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, or in beating upon ſome V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of Mettal that yields a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſound. The <hi>Chineſes</hi> have all ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Sports and Plays; they pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with Balls and Draughts, with Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and Cards; they are very dext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in ſtriking the Ball with their feet: Their manner is not to play in parties, only five or ſix meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and ſend with their feet th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ball from one to the other; I hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſeen a Ball continue a quarter of an hour without touching the Ground. Their Gardens are, for the moſt part incloſed Meadows, on purpoſe to e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe themſelves with a Ball. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y have no other ſweet ſcented flowers, but <hi>Jaſmin;</hi> their Roſes are very beautiful, but without any ſcer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They have alſo ſome Tulips, Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, and Gilliflowers; but they know not ſo much as the name of an Anemone: Nevertheleſs their
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:199150:39"/>Gardens are very green and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, becauſe of the conveniency of watering them with freſh Rivers; but they have but ſmall skill to dreſs and order them. All that I could take notice of, in ſuch places, was in the Kings Garden, where is to be ſeen a great Caſcade of Water, that falls from a Rock of Braſs, covered all over with artificial Trees of the ſame ſubſtance. The <hi>Chineſes</hi> are extraordinary skilful in the Art of caſting Mettals; therefore their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery is very beautiful.</p>
                  <p>We deſired him to inform us of ſomething concerning their other Arts, and cheifly concerning their Phyſick and Phyſitians.</p>
                  <p>Their Phyſitians, anſwered the Father, are notable in diſcerning by the Pulſe, the nature and qualities of a diſeaſe; but their knowledge is not ſo extraordinary in preſcribing remedies, for they govern themſelves by gueſs, at all adventures, as our Phyſitians.</p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:199150:40"/>
                  <p>I can ſpeak of both by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for when I fell ſick, about forty days diſtance from the City of <hi>Pekin,</hi> one of the Kings Phyſitians viſited me, at the requeſt of Father <hi>Adam Schall.</hi> As ſoon as he was come into my Chamber, he cauſed me to ſit down and ſuffered me to reſt quietly a while. Afterwards he uncovered both my Arms as far as the Elbows, placing them upon a Table, and felt the Pulſes of both Arms, one after another; preſſing the Arteries ſometimes hard, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſoftly, ſometimes equally; and at other times he preſt hard upon one Arm, leaving the other free: Sometimes he preſt hard upon one Pulſe, and ſoftly upon the other; he continued to feel it along while, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non he felt it but by turns; ſometimes he cauſed me to hold my fiſt cloſed, anon he made me open it. In ſhort, he felt and examined my Pulſe, as it did beat in every poſture of my
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:199150:40"/>Arm and Hand, which laſted a long while, about three quarters of an hour. After all this, I had almoſt a mind to diſcover to him my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe, but Father <hi>Adam</hi> interrupted me, and told me, that he knew it better then I did. When the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian was ſate down, he deſcribed with a wonderful majeſty my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and all its properties and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, aſſigning to them the time of their firſt beginning, in ſuch an exact manner, that I was ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſurpriſed. He appointed me ſome Potions, but by the ſmall advantage that I received from them, I found that he had been more skilful to gueſs at my diſeaſe, then to preſcribe Remedies. They never let any man blood, as we do, but inſtead of that, they make uſe of Cupping-Glaſſes in the Shoulders: They cure the Pox very well, with certain mixture of Herbs; ſo that this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is not ſo mortal, in theſe parts,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:199150:41"/>as in <hi>Turky, Perſia,</hi> and other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys of the <hi>Eaſt Indies:</hi> They have amongſt their Phyſicks a very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Root that grows, cheifly, in the Province of <hi>Sur-iven,</hi> they name it <hi>Tigers-Milk;</hi> for they ſay, That it never comes, but where the Milk of the ſhe <hi>Tigers</hi> hath moiſtened the ground, when they are furious and inraged by the purſuit of Hunts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. It is certain, that the ſmell of this Root is very like the ſmell of Milk, and its colour is white as Milk: They ſay, that when this Root is well prepared according to their skill, it is able to give an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible ſweat; it is true, I have ſeen the Root, but never the experiments of its vertues.</p>
                  <p>We queſtioned him afterwards, concerning the other Arts of the <hi>Chineſes;</hi> and the Father in the ſame order, as we had propoſed to him, returned us an anſwer to every queſtion.</p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:199150:41"/>
                  <p>That in <hi>China</hi> they have no Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal, but many Glaſſes, one ſort eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, which they name <hi>Rice-Glaſs,</hi> it is more brittle then our Glaſſes, but eaſier to work: For as ſoon as the ſubſtance of it feels the heat of the Furnace, it melts; and they are not unskilful in handling it, for they make with it moſt beautiful ſhapes and fabricks. Inſtead of Iron, they make uſe of great and hollow ſtaves of Glaſs, as our Enammellers in <hi>Europe.</hi> All their Looking-Glaſſes are very good; and as they have a particular Art in Melting and Caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mettals, they make many curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Looking-Glaſſes in a Concavity, for a very ſmall price; for a little above a peice, one may buy a Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Glaſs containing thirty two Thumbs in Diameter. The Jeſuites have carried to them the Art of making Spectacles and Teleſcopes. It is a wonderful thing that the <hi>Chineſes</hi> have humbled themſelves
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:199150:42"/>ſo much, as to learn this skill from us. At preſent they do them very well, according to our patterns which the Merchants of <hi>Europe</hi> tranſport thither. Our Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the larger ſize, is a gift well accepted of them; therefore the Merchants do not forget to furniſh them with this commodity.</p>
                  <p>They make excellent Stuffs with Thred of Gold, and with Golden Wire they make many beautiful Works: But they boaſt much of their Art in Gilding with Gold and Silver-Straw at the fire, in ſeveral manners; for with this gilded Straw they compoſe many rare and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Works. But I judge them to be moſt ingenious, in their making of artificial fires with Gunpowder; for they cauſe them to repreſent all kind of Shapes, Characters, Figures of Trees, and to appear in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of natural colours. I could never have believed from others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:199150:42"/>what my eyes have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced me to be true. I have ſeen at a Feaſt, a big Vine come down from the Roof of a large Room; and another fire after incompaſs it about, repreſenting its Leaves and Grapes ſo perfectly well, and ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally coloured, that a Painter could not have ſhewn one more lively.</p>
                  <p>This appearance laſted as long as we are repeating over our <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſereri;</hi> when the combuſtible mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was ſpent, the artificial Vine vaniſhed away, leaving behind a dark miſt in every place, where any part of the Vine had appeared with its Leaves and Branches of Grapes. They have ſomething of this Art in <hi>Perſia,</hi> but they cannot do ſuch wonderful feats as in <hi>China,</hi> for here they care not to communicate their skill: The expence is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, for forty ſhillings any man may have a fire repreſenting
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:199150:43"/>three or four ſhapes. At theſe words I inſtantly replied to Father <hi>Grue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> You make me now believe, what I could never credit before. About eleven years ago, I met at <hi>Rome</hi> with Monſieur <hi>Seſtel,</hi> a <hi>Dane,</hi> who told me, that ſome of his Friends had written to him from <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> that a <hi>Dane</hi> being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned out of <hi>China,</hi> had ſhewn the King an artificial Fire that roſe up into the Air, and burſt out into many flames, which repreſented the Kings name. The Father replied, You may ſafely believe it; but I wonder how this man could come to underſtand the myſtery, which he could never have been able to put in practice, unleſs he had tried it before, and taken an Oath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in all ſuch occaſions, I wonder alſo, how he could eſcape out of the Countrey after ſuch an Oath.</p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:199150:43"/>
                  <p>Monſieur <hi>Dati</hi> asked, Whether they uſe any Coaches or Chariots?</p>
                  <p>He anſwered, That the <hi>Chineſes</hi> are carried in Litters by Mules, or by Men; they are like ours, but ſomewhat longer; for they put in them, their Cloaths, a Bed, a Table, and other conveniencies for a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller. The <hi>Tartars</hi> have Coaches, with two Wheels, drawn by one or two Mules or Horſes. The Ladies of Viceroys, or of other eminent Lords, are drawn by two of theſe Beaſts, and incompaſſed about with a great many <hi>Tartarian</hi> Women on Horsback, Armed with Bow and Arrows. They carry their Bag and Baggage upon Camels backs, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a kind of carriage that hath but one great Wheel that turns in the midſt of two Trunks full of Stuff. One man draws this with a Girdle tied to his middle, and tied alſo to two Staves that are faſtned to the Trunks, with which he governs
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:199150:44"/>this Carriage at his pleaſure. They carry about their Wares and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities through the Land, in this manner.</p>
                  <p>We asked him, Whether they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in Hunting? Whether they run Races? Whether they be good Horſmen? And, whether they have any skill to manage Horſes?</p>
                  <p>He anſwered, That the <hi>Tartars</hi> are good Huntſmen, but the <hi>Chine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſeldom practice hunting: They know not what it is to run a Race; they are very careful and curious in harnaſſing well their Horſes, but they do not know how to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age them.</p>
                  <p>We deſired to know, Whether they took any Tobacco?</p>
                  <p>To this he replied, That they take no Tobacco in Powder, but in Smoak; the <hi>Tartars</hi> and the <hi>Chine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> the Men and the Women are great takers of Tobacco. For that purpoſe, the Women are commonly
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:199150:44"/>provided with a Bag that hangs over their ſhoulders, where their Pipe and their Tobacco is kept; but the Men carry their Pipes at their Gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles.</p>
                  <p>Monſieur <hi>Dati</hi> deſired to know, Whether the word <hi>Mandarin</hi> be of <hi>China?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He anſwered, That it was a <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugues,</hi> and that at <hi>China</hi> they are termed <hi>Quoan,</hi> which ſignifies a Prince, or a Governor.</p>
                  <p>We asked him concerning their Courage and Inclinations, to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial exploits and War.</p>
                  <p>He aſſured us, That they were Cowards, and that in three years time that he lived in <hi>China,</hi> he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver could ſee above two people fight together at cuffs; for they have no other way to ſatisfie their revenge, and end their quarrels.</p>
                  <p>We inquired of him, whether in his return he had not met with one Monſieur <hi>Tavernier,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:199150:45"/>that was gone from <hi>Legorne,</hi> about two years ſince, into the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> to carry thither a great deal of riches in Jewels; amongſt the reſt, he had a ſet of great Saphires, and of Pearls, as big as Pears, to make a Roſe, which he intended for the Great <hi>Mogol,</hi> to imbelliſh the Plume of his Elephant. I told him alſo, that Monſieur <hi>Tavernier</hi> had ſaid, That the Great <hi>Mogol</hi> did ſpend e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day Fifteen thouſand Crowns, only to keep the Elephants of the late King his Father. Therefore I deſired him to tell us, whether we were to believe any ſuch thing.</p>
                  <p>He aſſured us, That he had met with Monſieur <hi>Tavernier</hi> in <hi>Perſia,</hi> and that I might credit what he had told me, and much more concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the expence of this Prince to keep his Elephants.</p>
                  <p>That you may better underſtand the truth, you muſt know ſaid Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Grueber,</hi> That <hi>India</hi> beyond,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:199150:45"/>and on this ſide of the River <hi>Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> is divided into ſeveral diſtinct Regions or Governments, which are given by the Great <hi>Mogol,</hi> to the Lords of his Court, during life, upon condition of paying every year a certain ſum of money, as a Preſent or a Tribute. Beſides that, they are alſo obliged to keep al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, ſome a thouſand, others two thouſand men on foot, others five thouſand, which may be ready to march at the Emperors command. By this means it happens, that the number of their <hi>Militia</hi> never di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhes; and when the Prince comes to take a view of them, if the Soldiers be not well choſen, and of a good appearance, well cloathed and armed, their Cheiftains are in danger of Baniſhment from Court. Therefore the <hi>Mogol,</hi> may upon a ſudden, raiſe five or ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand men, ready for the encounter, without putting himſelf
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:199150:46"/>to any extraordinary expence; for every Governor is obliged to have all his <hi>Militia</hi> ready, in all times of the greateſt Peace. Now you muſt underſtand, that ſix or ſeven Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants are kept purpoſely to attend upon the perſon of the <hi>Mogol,</hi> they are named <hi>Panciaſari,</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies <hi>Lords of Five thouſands;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Great <hi>Mogol</hi> expends as much to keep them, as the Lords or Governors do, to entertain Five thouſand Horſe in the Army.</p>
                  <p>By this you may judge, that what Monſieur <hi>Tavernier</hi> has told you, is very true. But you may take notice, that the <hi>Mogol</hi> ſpends a great deal of this money in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fair Horſes, as well as Elephants. They are richly harnaſſed and ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with many precious Stones; the <hi>Mogol</hi> delights much to make them run Races.</p>
                  <p>He told us, that the preſent Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror in his young days, did ſeem
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:199150:46"/>to affect a retired life, ſpending his time in contemplation. But ſince this crafty Hypocrite hath caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his Mask, and pulled down his Father from his Throne, ſhutting him up in a priſon at <hi>Agra;</hi> the old man is about Eighty ſix years of Age: Only the fear of the Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his people, that did intirely love the Father, has hindered him from taking away his life. His pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is a very large Palace, with many Buildings about it, and pleaſant Gardens. He is there guarded by a numerous Company of Muskettiers, and attended upon by his Women that are kept in an adjoyning <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio,</hi> in which he ſpends, for the moſt part his time, and paſſeth the melancholly thoughts of his retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Emperor, his Son, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a high Tower to be built near to this place, in ſuch a manner, that it did overlook all the Gardens of his Father: Upon it he appointed a
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:199150:47"/>Watchman to overlook and ſpie out all that paſſed in the Priſon; but the old man cauſed him to be ſhot and killed by a Company of his Women: Then he deſired the cheif Commander of the Priſon, to tell his Son, from him, that he ſhould do well to ſend ſuch manner of Birds, and place them upon the ſame Tower, for they would give a great ſport to his Women.</p>
                  <p>The preſent <hi>Mogol,</hi> or Emperor, is renowned for many examples of Juſtice and Wiſdom, that are report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of him. It hapned when I was at <hi>Lahor,</hi> a Prince cauſed the Groom of his Stables to be killed in a very barbarous manner, his head to be ſtruck through with a large Nail, for a ſmall fault, for not having tended and dreſſed his beloved Horſe, as he ſhould have done. When the Emperor was ſitting in the Seat of Judicature, which he conſtantly doth every moneth, in a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:199150:47"/>day appointed for that purpoſe, in a great Meadow, out of the Royal City, the Grooms or Farrier Wife made her complaints of the cruel maſſacre of her Husband; the Great <hi>Mogol</hi> ſent immediately for the Prince, and asked him, If it were ſo as the Woman ſaid; He confeſſed his crime: Therefore the <hi>Mogol</hi> cauſed him to be ſtretched upon the Ground, and commanded the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or the Farriers Widow, to deal with him in the ſame manner as he had dealt with her deceaſed husband. There are many other reports con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Juſtice and Wiſdom of this Prince. He governs his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom very well, and cauſeth Juſtice to be adminiſtred, only to ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate himſelf with his Subjects, and prevent the tumults which they might otherwiſe be tempted to raiſe, becauſe of the cruel detention of his aged Father; for which unnatural deed, he knows that he is hated.</p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:199150:48"/>
                  <p>He is about forty years old, it may be when his Father ſhall be dead, he will looſe his preſent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and his forced Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons now impriſoned, by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations of Safety and Intereſt, may burſt out and diſcover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                  <p>In this manner Father <hi>Grueber</hi> anſwered to our Queſtions; we had a great deſire to inquire of other Matters, concerning that remote Countrey; but in regard our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation had laſted many hours, and that much of the night had been ſpent in this pleaſing diſcourſe, we thanked him for his great civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and withdrew to our Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:199150:48"/>
                  <head>Obſervations of the Travels of Father <hi>J. Grueber,</hi> taken out of the Letters which he hath written in Latine to <hi>Kircherus.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the Year One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty one, in the Moneth of <hi>June,</hi> theſe Fathers travelled out of <hi>Pekin,</hi> and in thirty days they arrived at <hi>Siganfú</hi> and from thence they went to <hi>Sining</hi> or <hi>Siningfu,</hi> in as many more, having twice paſſed the River <hi>Hoang.</hi> This City of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> or <hi>Siningfu,</hi> is a great City full of Inhabitants, ſcituate near the prodigious Wall of <hi>China;</hi> through its Gates all Merchants and Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, out of <hi>India,</hi> muſt paſs to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into <hi>Cathaia</hi> or <hi>China,</hi> and where they muſt reſt, until they have got, from the King, a Paſsport to proceed further.</p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:199150:49"/>
                  <p>This City is in Thirty ſix Degrees and ten Minutes from the Pole. From <hi>Sining</hi> they went in three Moneths time through <hi>Kalmuck,</hi> a Wilderneſs of <hi>Tartaria,</hi> to the Bord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Kingdom of <hi>Laſſa,</hi> which the <hi>Tartars</hi> call <hi>Barantola.</hi> This Wilderneſs is in ſome places Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainous, in others plain, full of Sand and Gravel; and therefore is barre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and unfruitful: Nevertheleſs, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath allowed ſome few Rivers to water it; upon their Banks there is very good Graſs for Cattle. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Deſart ſtretches it ſelf from t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Southern part of <hi>India,</hi> to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Northern, and is ſo large, that n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any body yet, that I could find did ever ſurvey its bounds; ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> think that it reacheth as far as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Frozen Seas. It hath many name<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>P. Marcus Venetus</hi> names it the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart of <hi>Lop,</hi> famous for the ordinar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> apparitions of Devils and Spirits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> but the Fathers of our Society mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:199150:49"/>no mention of it, although theſe Spirits have oftentimes diſcovered themſelves: He does not approve of their continuance and conſtant ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to all. The <hi>Tartars</hi> did an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently call it <hi>Belgian,</hi> afterwards <hi>Somo,</hi> the <hi>Chineſes Kalmuck,</hi> others <hi>Caracathai,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Black Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaia,</hi> where no Animal is to be ſeen but wilde Beeves of an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary bigneſs.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Tartars</hi> that are uſed to the Deſarts, venture through at any time; and when they come to the Rivers that afford any feeding for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heir Cattel, there they commonly pitch their Tents, capacious enough to ſhelter Man and Beaſt.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>Laſſa,</hi> otherwiſe named <hi>Barantola,</hi> ſituate in twenty nine degrees and ſix minutes from the Pole, they came in four days to the Foot of the Mountain <hi>Langur.</hi> This Mountain is one of the higheſt of the World; ſo that when Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:199150:50"/>paſs over its top, they can ſcarce draw their breath, becauſe of the ſubtilty of the Air. The breath of ſeveral venomous Herbs render a paſſage this way in Summer, to be very dangerous to our health. This Mountain is ſo full of grievous Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipices, and ſteep Rocks, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cart nor Horſe can paſs over it therefore all Paſſengers are force<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to march a foot, for a moneths time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> till they come to <hi>Cuth,</hi> the firſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Town of the Kingdom of <hi>Nekbal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> upon the Borders.</p>
                  <p>Although this Region is ſo moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainous and difficult to paſs ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Nature hath furniſhed it with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Springs of hot and of cold Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that burſt out of the Concavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Here is in ſome places plenty of Fiſh for Men, and Graſs for Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel. I think this is the Hilly Region which <hi>Ptolomy</hi> ſaith, that it lies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Mount <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> and ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it ſelf a great way into the Eaſt
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:199150:50"/>Countrey, and then divides into ranks of Hills; the one tends to the North, the other to the South. He calls it <hi>Parapaniſmus,</hi> and <hi>P. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Venetus, Belor.</hi> Other Nations do give other names to theſe Hills that border upon their ſeveral Countreys.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>Cuth,</hi> in five days journey, they came to the City <hi>Neſti,</hi> belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Kingdom of <hi>Nekbal,</hi> where the Inhabitants live in a moſt grievous Idolatry, without the leaſt knowledge of Chriſtianity. This place abounds in all manner of things neceſſary for the life of Man; ſo that you may have thirty or forty Hens for a crown.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>Nesti</hi> they travelled in ſix days, to the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Nekbal,</hi> called <hi>Cadmendu,</hi> lying in twenty ſeven degrees and five minutes from the Pole. The King is a great Prince, and a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, but no Enemy to Chriſtianity.</p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:199150:51"/>
                  <p>From <hi>Cadmendu,</hi> in half a day, they went to <hi>Nekbal,</hi> the cheif City of the Kingdom, which is called alſo <hi>Baddan;</hi> and from thence, in five days, they arrived at the City <hi>Hedonda,</hi> belonging to the Kingdom of <hi>Maranga,</hi> ſituate in twenty ſix degrees and thiry ſix minutes from the Pole. From thence, in eight days, Travellers go to <hi>Mutgari,</hi> the firſt City upon the confines of the Kingdom of <hi>Mogol.</hi> From <hi>Mutgari,</hi> they went to <hi>Battana,</hi> a Town of the Kingdom of <hi>Bengala,</hi> ſituate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the River <hi>Ganges,</hi> in twenty five degrees and forty four minutes. From <hi>Battana,</hi> in eight days, they came to <hi>Benares,</hi> a populous Town near the River <hi>Ganges,</hi> lying in twenty four degrees and fifty mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes. It is a noted place, for there are the Schools of the <hi>Brachmans,</hi> where all the Sciences, profeſſed in thoſe Countreys, are taught, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:199150:51"/>with them, the moſt abominable Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>Benares,</hi> there are eight days journey, to <hi>Catampor;</hi> and from thence to <hi>Agra,</hi> ſeven more.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>Pekin</hi> to <hi>Agra,</hi> Men go in 214 days. But when they go no faſter then the <hi>Carravans,</hi> they are four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen moneths in their journey.</p>
                  <p>This Relation I had from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of our Society, who gave me this account of their Journeys.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Kingdoms were never known by any in <hi>Europe</hi> before, nor to the Geographers. In their paſſage they took notice of many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars concerning the Cuſtoms and Manners of the ſeveral Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>Pekin,</hi> the Imperial City of <hi>China,</hi> they travelled in two moneths to the famous Walls of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, where the great City <hi>Sining<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fu</hi> is ſituate, as a ſtrong Bulwark againſt the <hi>Tartars</hi> invaſions. They
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:199150:52"/>took great notice of the Walls, that are as ſtrongly built, as the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies of that place will afford. This Wall is ſo large, that ſix Horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men may ride upon it, in a breſt, without hindering one another. They are often viſited by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Siningfú,</hi> to receive the benefit of the freſh Air, which comes off from the Sandy Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of the Neighboring Deſart; and to exerciſe themſelves in walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and delighting their eyes, with the pleaſant Proſpects; for they are ſo high, that they diſcover the Countrey round about, and invite the Citizens to take a view of the delightful objects that appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them: There is a very eaſie aſcent up to this high Wall.</p>
                  <p>Its length from this City, to the other Gate, by which Men come out of the Deſarts into the Town of <hi>Sucien,</hi> is about eighteen days journey; many, out of curioſity, as
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:199150:52"/>well as out of neceſſity of buſineſs, undertake this journey. For that purpoſe they get a Paſsport from the Governor of <hi>Siningfú,</hi> and provide themſelves with ſufficient victuals. They ſay, that in this delightful pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, they may ſee an infinite number of dwellings in their way, in the <hi>China</hi> ſide, which they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover as from a high Mountain; but on the other ſide, towards the great and ſpacious Wilderneſs, as the Inhabitants have told them, there are all manner of wilde Beaſts to be ſeen, <hi>Tigers, Lions, Elephants, Rhinocerots, Leopards, Wilde Bulls, Monocerots;</hi> this laſt ſort are a kind of <hi>Aſſes</hi> with Horns in their Fronts. The beholders may from hence, without fear of danger, pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with many ſtrange and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual ſights of furious Beaſts, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially from that part of the Wall that is towards the South, in the moſt inhabited places near to <hi>Quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:199150:53"/>Junnam,</hi> and <hi>Tibet.</hi> From hence to the Yellow River, in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey adjoyning to the Wall, the wild Beaſts hunt together in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies to ſeek for food in theſe places that are full of Brambles and Buſhes.</p>
                  <p>When the Fathers of our Society were gone out of this prodigious Wall, into the Neighboring Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, they found a ſmall Stream of Water full of Fiſh, whereof they dreſſed a great quantity in their Tent, and kep ſome for another time. When they were paſſed over the Yellow River which runs out of the Wall, they entered into that vaſt Deſart of <hi>Kalmak,</hi> full of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful Mountains, and Fields moſt dreadful to behold; and in three moneths they arrived at the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Barantola.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Although this Wilderneſs be ſo ſolitary, and uninhabitable, it is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented by the <hi>Tartars</hi> of <hi>Kalmuk,</hi> at certain times of the year, when
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:199150:53"/>the Graſs appears upon the ſides of the Rivers; then they tranſport their Portable Houſes or Tents, and pitch them in ſuch numbers toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that any man would judge every company to be a City.</p>
                  <p>Theſe <hi>Tartars</hi> take the liberty to march up and down, and plunder all that they can meet with; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is neceſſary to be well armed againſt the violences of theſe Rogues, and to travel with a good <hi>Caravan.</hi> Our Fathers did often light upon ſeveral ſcattered com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of them, as they travelled through this Wilderneſs.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Lamae,</hi> who are the Prieſts of theſe <hi>Tartars</hi> of <hi>Kalmak,</hi> are diſtinguiſhable by a Red Hat, a White Gown twiſted behind, a Red Girdle, and a Yellow Tunick: At their Girdle there is a Purſe that is faſtned to it. They ſay, that the <hi>Tartars</hi> of <hi>Kalmak</hi> are cloathed with Skins, and a Yellow Cap;
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:199150:54"/>their Women with Skins, or with Green or Red Stuffs; every one of them hath a Charm and Characters hung about their Necks, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect them from evil ſpirits and witchcraft. They lodge in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nermoſt Room of the Tent, made up with portable Staves, but the outſide is covered with a thick Wollen Cloath and tied with Ropes. When their <hi>Lamae</hi> are at their Devotions, their Bigots, there preſent, roul about a Wheel, and handle it as a Scepter.</p>
                  <p>They have given the deſcription of <hi>Han,</hi> a deceaſed King of <hi>Tanguth,</hi> whom they ſay had fourteen Sons, and for his Goodneſs and Juſtice in governing his Kingdom, the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants have honored him as a god, in their Countrey faſhion. He is ſaid to have been of a Tawny coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, he had a Beard of a Cheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut colour, and Eyes like unto Dogs-eyes, ſwelling out of his Head.</p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:199150:54"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tanguth</hi> is a large Kingdom of <hi>Tartaria,</hi> theſe Father-Jeſuites have travelled through a great part of it.</p>
                  <p>At that time, in the Court of <hi>Dena,</hi> King of <hi>Tanguth,</hi> there was a Woman came from the Northern part of <hi>Tartary,</hi> that wore twiſted Hair, in the manner of Ropes; her Head was adorned with Sea-ſhells, and her middle bound about with a Girdle. In the ſame place, ſome of the Courtiers were habited as Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, only their Cloaths were of a Red colour as their Prieſts.</p>
                  <p>Into theſe Kingdoms of <hi>Tanguth</hi> and <hi>Barantola,</hi> the Devils ſubtilty hath brought in a moſt abominable and horrid cuſtom. They chuſe a ſtrong youth, ſtout, and luſty, and give him liberty at certain times of the year, to kill, with the weapons, that he hath for that purpoſe, Men, Women, and Children, that he meets in his way; and when they are
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:199150:55"/>killed in this manner, they imagine that they are conſecrated to their goddeſs <hi>Menipe,</hi> that they are in a moſt happy eſtate; and therefore the living render to their memories, particular honors.</p>
                  <p>The youth is cloathed with a Garment of ſeveral colours, he is furniſhed with a Sword, with Bow, Arrows, and a Quiver; he carries ſometimes a Banner. At a certain ſeaſon, he is tranſported with Fury, and poſſeſſed by the Spirit, unto whom he is conſecrated; he flies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Streets, and rambles up and down; all that he meets, he kills, for none dare make him any reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
                  <p>This youth they call, in their Tongue, <hi>Buth,</hi> which word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a <hi>Slayer.</hi> Whiles the Fathers were there, they had a ſight of him habited in that manner as he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready deſcribed.</p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:199150:55"/>
                  <p>In this large Kingdom of <hi>Tanguth,</hi> there are many Kingdoms included, firſt, <hi>Barantola,</hi> which is alſo called <hi>Laſſa,</hi> the name of the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of that Kingdom. It hath a King of its own, miſerably addicted to Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm. He worſhips many Heathen Idols, amongſt whom <hi>Menipe</hi> is one of the cheif. Its head riſeth up as a Sugar-loaf, in a monſtrous manner. <hi>Kircherus</hi> hath promiſed to publiſh a diſcourſe, more at large, of this and other Idols of <hi>China.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Before this Idol, theſe people per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their Sacrifices with ſtrange geſtures, often repeating this excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>O Manipe mi hum, ô Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipe mi hum,</hi> that is, <hi>Manipe ſave us.</hi> Beſides, theſe fooliſh Idolaters bring to their Idol, to ingratiate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with him, all kind of Meats; and obſerve many other abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable practices of the antient Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:199150:56"/>
                  <p>There is another Image of a falſe God to be ſeen in <hi>Barantola,</hi> which is ſo ſtrange, that ſcarce any body will believe it; therefore I ſhall here give a more punctual account of it.</p>
                  <p>The ſaid Fathers, <hi>Grueber</hi> and <hi>d'Orville</hi> affirm, that whiles they waited at <hi>Barantola,</hi> about two Moneths, until a <hi>Caravan</hi> was ready to march, they took great notice of the Peoples Manners and Cuſtoms, whereof ſome were ridiculous, and ſome moſt abominable.</p>
                  <p>In this Kingdom there are two Kings, the one is imployed about the Government of the Kingdom, and is named <hi>Dena;</hi> the other is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired from all worldly affairs; he lives idle in the ſecret Chambers of his Pallace, and is adored and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped as a god; not only by the Natives, but alſo by all the Kings of <hi>Tartaria,</hi> ſubject to this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; for they come to him in pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:199150:56"/>They name him their eternal and heavenly Father, and reverence him as the true and living God, by offering to him great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents. He ſits in an obſcure and dark place of his Pallace, adorned with Gold and Silver, upon a Bed raiſed on high; under his feet rich Carpets are ſpred, and round about him many Lamps ſtand lighted. When ſtrangers come to him, they fall upon their faces, they creep to him upon their knees, and kiſs his feet, as the Papiſts do the toes of their Pope, with a wonderful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</p>
                  <p>From hence we may diſcover the Devils ſubtilty, in appropriating this ceremony and teſtimony of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect due to none on Earth, but to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Here Mr. <hi>Jeſuite</hi> ſpeaks as a Papiſt.</note> to the barbarous Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions of this Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Nation. He hath had the malice to transfer and uſurp all the other
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:199150:57"/>myſteries of our Faith to his own Worſhip. As the Papiſts call the Pope, the Father of all Spiritual Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; ſo theſe Idolaters call this Demy-God, <hi>The great Lama,</hi> or <hi>The High Prieſt,</hi> or <hi>The Lama of Lamas;</hi> that is, The Prieſt of Prieſts: For all their Religion and Idolatry de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon him; therefore they honor him with the title of <hi>Eternal Father.</hi> And that by his deceaſe, his weakneſs and mortality might not appear, the Inferior <hi>Lamae,</hi> and other Prieſts only are admitted to attend upon him, to procure him whatſoever he ſtands in need of, to receive his commands, and deliver them as Oracles of the Divinity to the ſimple Pilgrims.</p>
                  <p>Theſe men after his death, are wont to ſeek another, as like him in feature and ſtature as they can; him they lift upon the Throne. By this means the whole Kingdom, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with the manner of the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:199150:57"/>deceit, firmly believes that he is riſen again to them, from the dead, ſeven times; and that he ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for ever. This perſwaſion is ſo fixed in their minds, blinded with the Devils illuſions and deceits, that there is none queſtions it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is worſhipped by all in a ſignal manner. Every one eſteems him happy indeed, who can prevail ſo much upon the goodneſs of the inferior <hi>Lamae,</hi> his attendants, as to get ſomething that hath but touched his body, or been taken from him, which they bear about their necks. For that purpoſe they load them with many rich gifts to obtain this their deſire. O abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and filthy blindneſs! By theſe Relicks, they imagine themſelves protected againſt all manner of evils.</p>
                  <p>This the ſaid Fathers under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, to their great grief, from the Inhabitants of <hi>Barantola.</hi> It is true,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:199150:58"/>the Fathers did not ſee this great <hi>Lama,</hi> becauſe none is admitted that makes profeſſion of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion; and there are many previous Ceremonies full of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry to be practiced, before any man can be permitted to go near him, but they ſaw his Picture at the Entry in of the Kings Palace; unto which, as much reverence is paid, when but repreſented in Pictures and Images, as if he were there in perſon, by theſe Idolaters. His au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is ſo great all over <hi>Tartaria,</hi> that there is no King that offers to take upon him his royal Scepter, but he ſends firſt his Ambaſſadors with rich preſents to the great <hi>Lama,</hi> to obtain his bleſſing for his happy and proſperous reign.</p>
                  <p>They ſaw alſo at <hi>Barantola</hi> ſome ſtrange Women, of a Neighbor King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom called <hi>Coïn,</hi> one old and the other young: Women of an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Nobility fold up their Hair in a
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:199150:58"/>bundle, and caſt them behind their backs. Upon their foreheads they wear a red Ribbon, adorned with Pearl, but on their heads a Silver Crown, in the ſhape of a Box, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſhed with <hi>Turkoiſes</hi> and <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They arrived next from <hi>Baranto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> to the Kingdom of <hi>Nekbal,</hi> through a difficult way that leads over one of the higheſt Mountains of the World, named <hi>Langur,</hi> which we have already deſcribed. They found all things there needful to the life of Man, but only the knowledge of Chriſtianity; for the Natives are all involved in the thick miſts of the Heathens ignorance.</p>
                  <p>The cheif Towns are <hi>Cuthi</hi> and <hi>Nesti;</hi> the Cuſtome of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants is, when any drink to Women, other perſons pour into the Cup their liquor called <hi>Chà,</hi> or Wine, three times, and obſerve other ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous ceremonies.</p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:199150:59"/>
                  <p>There is another cuſtome practiſed here moſt horrid and barbarous, they bring out into the open field, and leave upon the ground, in the cold and wet, without any pitty, ſuch as are deſperately ſick and near death; and when they are dead they ſuffer them to be devoured by the wild Fowl, by the Wolves and Dogs; for they look upon this namely the ſtomachs of living Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, to be the moſt glorious Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that their dead Corps ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pretend to. The Women of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Kingdom are ſo ugly and deforme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that they ſeem to be Devils, rathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> then humane Creatures: For the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> never waſh themſelves for Religio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſake, but anoint themſelves wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> an oyl, noiſome to our ſmells, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> cauſeth them to ſtink moſt intol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rably to all ſtrangers, and cov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> them over with ſuch frightful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pearances, that one would t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:199150:59"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hem to be Witches, and Devils in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umane ſhapes.</p>
                  <p>The King was very kind to theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>athers, cheifly becauſe they gave <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im ſome Proſpective Glaſſes, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e had never ſeen before, and ſome other curious trifles which ſurpriſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m in ſuch a manner, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lved to detain theſe Fathers with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m, and would not ſuffer them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>epart, until they had ſolemnly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>omiſed to return; which if they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d, he ingaged to aſſign them an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouſe, which he would build for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eir uſe, to allow them a ſufficient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>elihood, and full liberty to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gate their faith in any part of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ngdom.</p>
                  <p>When they departed out of <hi>Nek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l,</hi> they entered into the Confines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the Kingdom of <hi>Maranga,</hi> which orders upon that of <hi>Tebet,</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eif Town is <hi>Rodok,</hi> the uttermoſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ounds of the Travels of Father <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>andrada.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:199150:60"/>
                  <p>They found here ſome ſigns o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſtianity, by the names of <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, Anthony,</hi> and <hi>Dominicus, &amp;c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> which made them conjecture, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> our Religion had been heretofore profeſſed in this place. From hence they travelled to the firſt City <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Mogols</hi> Kingdom, named <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>donda;</hi> and from thence to <hi>Battani</hi> a City upon the River <hi>Gange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and then to <hi>Benares,</hi> the Academy of the <hi>Brachmans;</hi> afterwards the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> went to <hi>Agra,</hi> the Royal Palla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the <hi>Mogol.</hi> Father <hi>Albertus d'O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ville,</hi> ſick and weary of his trave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling died within a few days after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> arrival, in this middle way betwee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>China</hi> and <hi>Europe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:199150:60"/>
                  <p>THE Moſt Remarkable PASSAGES OF <hi>The Life and Reign</hi> OF <hi>LEWIS</hi> XIV.</p>
                  <p>The Preſent KING IN FRANCE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Lownds,</hi> over againſt <hi>Exeter-Houſe</hi> in the <hi>Strand.</hi> 1675.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb facs="tcp:199150:61"/>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:199150:61"/>
                  <head>The moſt noted Paſſages of the Raign of the <hi>French</hi> King.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies ſeldom live long in Peace. Either the Intereſt of the Kingdoms, or the jealouſies of State, or the humors of the People, or the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural averſions and animoſities which they have received by inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance from their Forefathers, do frequently kindle the flames of War. Their Neighborhood and continual Converſation furniſhes them with many occaſions of diſtaſtes and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:199150:62"/>for both the <hi>Spaniard</hi> and the <hi>French,</hi> have no compliance nor reſpect for one another. They are naturally proud and high-minded, they pretend both to the Univerſal Monarchy, and think all the World muſt bow and creep to their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. I intend not to examine in this ſhort Tract, the cauſes of their frequent Ruptures and Wars, I ſhall confine my diſcourſe within the Borders of the <hi>French</hi> Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, where we muſt viſit the King and Court, and ſee what hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned worthy of our obſervation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that famous Theater of <hi>Europe.</hi> I deſign not ſo much to ſatisfie the <hi>Readers</hi> curioſity, as to furniſh him with that knowledge which he may improve to his advantage; for in every capacity true and impartial Hiſtory tends to our right informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and direction, God by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence teacheth men as well as by his Word. It concerns us not to
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:199150:62"/>neglect the means that he affords for our inſtruction. And there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more required in men that pretend to learning and perfection, then to be acquainted with the late and preſent Affairs, as well as with thoſe that we have received from our Forefathers Relations.</p>
                  <p>It is very obſervable, that the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſeldom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude Peace without a Marriage. The old Fable of <hi>Mars</hi>'s Adultery or Conjunction with <hi>Venus,</hi> is a practice ſo ordinary amongſt them, that it needs no proof. In the year One thouſand ſix hundred and fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen, the Polititians of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms were reſolved to conclude their diſputes, and reunite their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts in a Marriage between <hi>Lewis</hi> the Thirteenth, ſirnamed <hi>The Juſt,</hi> and <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Austria, Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain.</hi> Both Kingdoms expected from theſe two hopeful Princes, a numerous poſterity; but to the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:199150:63"/>great diſappointment of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and of all <hi>Europe,</hi> they lived together three and twenty years without Children. Succeſs follows not always our beſt endeavors. At laſt in the Moneth of <hi>September,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred thirty and eight, the Queen was brought to Bed of a brave luſty Boy, who was ſaluted and welcomed into the World by the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> with the name of <hi>Dieu-donnè, Given of God:</hi> For they were verily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that his Birth and Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had been miraculous, in regard of the indiſpoſition of his Father. To ſtrengthen this perſwaſion, the more by Cardinal <hi>Mazarines</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance, then the <hi>Factotum</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> the King, the Queen, and the whole Court had been in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, with much devotion, bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>footed, to the Chappel of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> near <hi>Paris,</hi> to deſire from her, a Son and Heir to the Crown o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:199150:63"/>
                     <hi>France.</hi> Therefore the <hi>French</hi> look upon this Prince, as the effect and return of their Prayers, then ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly offered up to the Bleſſed Virgin; for within a year after, the King and Queen were bleſſed with this hopeful Child, to the greater joy of <hi>France,</hi> then of ſome of the Blood Royal, who had promiſed to themſelves the Kingdom, in caſe <hi>Lewis</hi> the Thirteenth did die with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iſſue. Their diſcontents remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed long concealed in private, and were not ſuffered to break out into a Publick War, by the good order that the Cardinal gave to the Affairs of the Kingdom, and by their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for the King, then alive. But afterwards, when they ſaw <hi>Lewis</hi> in his Grave, the People diſſatisfied, and the Grandees diſcontented, with the <hi>Italian</hi> Government, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed their diſpleaſures at the Head of an Army, with the loud noiſe of Drums, Trumpets, and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:199150:64"/>Cannon; as we ſhall ſee by and by.</p>
                  <p>As ſoon as the <hi>Dolphin</hi> was inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurated into his Principality, and initiated into Chriſtian Religion, they gave him his Attendants and Officers, according to his quality and Birth; the two cheif were his Governeſs — a Lady of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpirit, and <hi>Hardouin de Perefixe,</hi> afterwards Biſhop of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and ſince removed to the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Paris,</hi> was his Governor and Tutor. He is a great Polititian, Wiſe, and Learned, very affable and courteous. Whiles he lay in his Cradle, we can find nothing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of our notice, but as ſoon as he ſtept out of it to walk alone, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence waited upon him, to put into his hands a Scepter, before he could manage it: For at four years of age, and a few Moneths, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Lewis,</hi> ſirnamed <hi>The Just,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted this life, having publiſhed
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:199150:64"/>before his Declaration, dated <hi>April</hi> 21. 1643. By which the Queen was appointed Regent, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneſs of the whole Kingdom, the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> was her Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and cheif of the Council. The Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> deceaſed, the Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> Monſieur <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guier,</hi> Chancellor of <hi>France,</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Bouthillier,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigny;</hi> were to be of this Privy Council; but the conduct of the Army, then on foot, was left to the Duke of <hi>Enguien,</hi> who is now Prince of <hi>Condé.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Declaration ſettled the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Kingdom, and prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the miſcheif which might have hapned, in caſe the election of theſe great Officers of State had been left to the choice of ſuch as might have deſigned to imbroil the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, for their own private ends. About a Moneth after, on the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of <hi>May,</hi> 1643. the King
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:199150:65"/>died. At that time the <hi>Spaniard</hi> was attempting to inlarge his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions in the <hi>Low Countreys,</hi> by a War with <hi>France.</hi> Don <hi>Franciſco de Melo</hi> was Viceroy there, at the Head of an Army before <hi>Rocroy,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Garriſon, which he beſieged in vain: For the Duke of <hi>Enguien,</hi> a young General, of twenty two years of age, came ſeaſonably to its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, forced the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, and obtained of them a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table victory on the nineteenth of <hi>May.</hi> All their Artillery was taken, with about threeſcore Colours; all their Bag and Baggage, and ſix thouſand priſoners: The Colours were ſent to <hi>Paris,</hi> to be preſented to the new King, ſix days after his promotion to the Throne. The Viceroy behaved himſelf like a great Commander, he incouraged his men by his words, promiſes, and example; where he perceived the greateſt danger, there did he hazard
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:199150:65"/>his perſon, and his life; but when he ſaw the day loſt, and the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſlaughter of his Soldiers, he found a way out of his Trenches, to retreat with the ſad remains of his broken Army, and left his Enemy to glory in their Succeſs, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich themſelves with his ſpoils. The Count <hi>de Fontaines</hi> was then grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly incommoded with a diſeaſe; nevertheleſs, for the honor of his Maſter, he cauſed himſelf to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in a Chair, during the fight, that he might aſſiſt his men with his Counſels, and incouragement; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he could not help them by his example. He purchaſed to himſelf much renown with the loſs of his life; for he reſolved to overcome or die. Therefore in the hurry and rout of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whom he labored to keep to their Colours, he was killed by a mean hand.</p>
                  <p>This victory gave a check to the deſigns of the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:199150:66"/>inlarging their Borders upon <hi>France.</hi> They had perſwaded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that the <hi>French</hi> had been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, during the ſickneſs of the old King; and that they were not ſo able to make reſiſtance in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority of the new; for commonly, Factions and private Intereſts, raign in all Courts and Armies, when the Prince hath not attained to the age and ability of managing his own affairs. But it hath been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that when men intend to advantage themſelves by their Neighbors weakneſs, they find themſelves diſappointed at laſt, for providence makes uſe of the feebleſt and moſt contemptible Agents to defeat the proudeſt purpoſes.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>French</hi> General purſued the Enemy into his own Countrey, and took, from him, ſeveral ſmall Forts and Towns, as <hi>Maubeuge, Borle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont, Aimmerikt, Binch,</hi> and <hi>Thion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville, &amp;c.</hi> So that they that had
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:199150:66"/>flattered themſelves of enjoying new Conqueſts, loſt a ſmall portion of their own Land. The Caſtle and Town of <hi>Cirke</hi> ſtopped the courſe of the victorious General; it was ſo well furniſhed with Men and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, and commanded by ſuch a reſolute Governor, that the threats of the <hi>French</hi> Army, the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency of an approaching Siege, and the noiſe of the thundering Cannon, could not prevail upon him to yield to the firſt Summons, therefore it held out againſt the <hi>French</hi> ſeveral days; but when they had brought their Trenches to the Town Walls, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Conditions of Surrendring it up.</p>
                  <p>After this, the Duke of <hi>Enguien</hi> left the Army, about the latter end of <hi>August,</hi> to receive the Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Court at <hi>Paris,</hi> for his great ſucceſs in <hi>Flanders;</hi> but at his firſt arrival, the news of the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:199150:67"/>death of the Mareſchal <hi>de Guebri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant,</hi> General of the <hi>French</hi> Forces in <hi>Germany,</hi> haſtned him thither. He had been ingaged in a Battle againſt the Imperialiſts, on the ſeventeenth of <hi>November,</hi> where he was mortal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wounded; for he died a few days after. The fight had been deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate between the <hi>Germans,</hi> and the <hi>French,</hi> both loſt a great many of their beſt men; ſo that the <hi>French</hi> Army was not able to hold the Field any longer, without the coming in of freſh and victorious Troops out of <hi>Flanders,</hi> with their young Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Enguien.</hi> His coming reſtored heart and courage to the ſhattered Companies of the dead Mareſchals Army. The <hi>French,</hi> who are always wont to boaſt much in their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes and Victories, and ſeldom or never to grant the loſs of the day to their triumphing Enemies, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That the Mareſchal beat the <hi>Germans</hi> out of the Field. It is
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:199150:67"/>certain they ſeiſed, a little after, upon <hi>Rotueil,</hi> a Frontier-Town, where the wounded Mareſchal breathed forth his laſt gaſp.</p>
                  <p>This War between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> had ingaged moſt Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> in the quarrel, the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets ſounded round about the Borders, in <hi>Savoy,</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre, Catalonia, Flanders, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, Alſatia, &amp;c.</hi> Armies and Armed Men did carry about, Death and Deſtruction.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Italy,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> had three watchful Commanders, Prince <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> took from the <hi>Spaniard, Trin;</hi> the Marqueſs of <hi>Ville</hi> ſeiſed upon <hi>Aſt;</hi> and the Count of <hi>Pleſſis-Praſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> invaded <hi>Estura,</hi> ſmall places that would deſerve no mention, if theſe Generals had but taken any more conſiderable Towns; but for want of ſtronger and more noted Garriſons, and braver exploits, the <hi>French</hi> muſt needs ſtuff their Relations
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:199150:68"/>with the taking of theſe poor Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets. And the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> on their ſide, were not idle, they gained ſeveral places upon the <hi>French,</hi> but none of any importance.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Catalonia,</hi> the Mareſchal <hi>de la Mouthe Houdancour</hi> commanded as Viceroy, for the <hi>French,</hi> at the head of a ſmall Army, with which, he drove the <hi>Spaniards</hi> from the Siege of <hi>Miravel</hi> and <hi>Flix;</hi> he made ſome inroads into the Kingdom of <hi>Arragon,</hi> and ſeiſed upon <hi>Almeras.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the ſame year, at Sea, as well as at Land, the affairs of War were carried on with much heat: The Duke of <hi>Brezè</hi> was Admiral for the <hi>French,</hi> in the <hi>Streights.</hi> He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, with his Light Squadrons, againſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet, twice, once before <hi>Carthagena,</hi> in the Moneth of <hi>August;</hi> and another time, on the nineth day of <hi>September.</hi> In both Rencounters, the <hi>Armadoes</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed a few Bullets, looked one
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:199150:68"/>another in the face; but they were ſo ſcared with their Enemies fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful countenances, and with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of what might happen, if they continued too obſtinately in the fight, that they were both willing to part upon equal terms; although the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniard</hi> both claim the Victory as their own.</p>
                  <p>When the War is once kindled between theſe two Nations, it is not one or two Campagnes can put a period to their diſputes; no leſs then a River of the Subjects Blood muſt be ſpilled, to extinguiſh the flames. And it is obſervable, that all their Neighbors muſt dance at the ſound of their Fiddles, and be intereſted in their quarrels. All the Nations of <hi>Europe</hi> muſt attend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and ſecond their bloody deſigns. War like a Tempeſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly riſeth out of <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> then it ſpreds it ſelf, and involves
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:199150:69"/>all the Neighborhood into the ſame miſery. Both Kingdoms are ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous and conſiderable, that when the Princes of either ſtir, all the bordering people move; they are forced in their own defence to have their Armies ready; which when they are ſo, Intereſt obliges them to employ them.</p>
                  <p>During this Winter, great prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations were making for the enſuing Spring of the year 1644. As ſoon as it appeared, the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> was appointed to command in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> where he beſieged <hi>Graveling,</hi> which was ſurrendered to him, after a ſtout reſiſtance of two moneths: He made his entry the Twenty nineth of <hi>July.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This place was ſtrong and well fortified, and the Key of <hi>Flanders,</hi> on that ſide; therefore the taking of it, did as much rejoyce the <hi>French,</hi> as it did grieve the <hi>Spaniard.</hi> After this ſucceſs, the Mareſchal of
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:199150:69"/>
                     <hi>Gaſſion,</hi> Lieutenant General, had orders to march with his Army fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the Enemies Countrey, where he took and pillaged ſome ſmall Caſtles, the Abby of <hi>Vate,</hi> the Forts of <hi>Rebus, d'Henuin,</hi> and <hi>Arq.</hi> Some few <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Troops that were ſo unhappy as to come within his reach, were put to flight.</p>
                  <p>In the mean while, the Duke of <hi>Enguien</hi> was General in <hi>Germany;</hi> for that Countrey hath always been the Seat of War, when any is ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in <hi>Europe.</hi> At this time, the whole Houſe of <hi>Austria</hi> that have ſo great a ſway in that Climat, thought themſelves ingaged to aſſiſt the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> their Brother, againſt the common Enemy the <hi>French.</hi> General <hi>Merci</hi> commanded the Army of the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> he was ſo ſucceſsful to take <hi>Frie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> from the <hi>French.</hi> As he was marching farther, to beſiege ſome other place, the Duke of <hi>Enguien</hi>
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:199150:70"/>met him with his Army, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged three times on three ſeveral days; at laſt, the <hi>French</hi> forced them, after a notable ſlaughter, to a diſorderly retreat. After this, many conſiderable Towns ſubmitted to the conquering valor of the Duke of <hi>Enguien,</hi> and received, from him, Garriſons only to preſerve their Territories from the ſpoil, which otherwiſe he would have made. <hi>Philipsbourgh,</hi> a ſtrong Frontier Town, <hi>Vormes, Spire, Mayence, Burghen, Landau,</hi> and the Caſtle of <hi>Magdebourgh,</hi> were yielded up this Summer.</p>
                  <p>But before the year was over, the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> agreed to ſend all their Plenipotentiaries to <hi>Munster,</hi> there to compoſe their differences, and agree in a General Peace; for <hi>Germany,</hi> and the Frontier Towns of the Empire had been ſo much impoveriſhed; by the long and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Wars, that as many died by
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:199150:70"/>Famine, as formerly by the Sword. The only remedy was an Univerſal Peace, which was endeavored be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween all the Princes of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. The Queen Regent of <hi>France,</hi> ſent thither the Count <hi>d' Avaux,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Servien,</hi> to manage the <hi>French</hi> intereſt; afterwards the Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi> followed. The Treaty began in the Moneth of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril,</hi> 1644. but could not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded till the Twenty fourth of <hi>October,</hi> 1648. All the Monarchs of <hi>Europe</hi> agreed to lay down Arms, and to ſuffer their People to injoy the Bleſſings of Peace, only <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> had ſuch differences as could not be compoſed, their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions were ſo high, and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled, That the greateſt Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians that aſſiſted at this compoſure of Affairs, could not find any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to bring them to an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Therefore the Miniſters of other Princes did their buſineſs
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:199150:71"/>without them. When they ſaw them ſo ſtiff, in not yielding to one another, they left them to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their Maſters alone, to end their own quarrels, and fight till they were weary. That which adminiſtered new difficulties every day to this Peace, between the two Monarchies, was the proſecution of the War, which was ſo vigorouſly managed by the <hi>French,</hi> in the time of the Treaty, that in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Spring, 1645. they had five Armies on foot, in <hi>Flanders,</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> in <hi>Lorraine,</hi> in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> and in <hi>Italy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Army of <hi>Flanders</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> as <hi>Generaliſſimo;</hi> his Lieutenants were the Mareſchals <hi>de Gaſſion,</hi> and <hi>Rant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zau:</hi> At their paſſage over the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of <hi>Colme,</hi> there was a very hot diſpute between the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniards;</hi> but, in fine, the two Mareſchals behaved themſelves ſo
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:199150:71"/>bravely, that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> was put to flight, and the paſſage opened. <hi>Mardike, Bourbourgh, Lillers, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thune, Mount-Caſſel, S. Venant, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenes,</hi> and <hi>Armentiers,</hi> were forced to yield. The Town of <hi>Lens</hi> was ſuddenly taken.</p>
                  <p>Upon the Borders of <hi>Germany,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Enguien,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> General, marched with his Troops as far as the <hi>Nekar,</hi> he took <hi>Rotem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourgh,</hi> and went next to find out his Enemies, the United Forces of the Empire, that were encamped about <hi>Nortlinguen,</hi> and <hi>Dunkeſpiel.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> had here a notable victory, Four thouſand men were killed, with <hi>Merci,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Bavariaes</hi> General; <hi>Gleen,</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors General was taken, with all the Proviſions, Artillery, Waggons, and above forty Colours. The Duke entertained <hi>Gleen</hi> very kindly, and ſet him at liberty; the Neighbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Towns, <hi>Nortlinguen</hi> and <hi>Dunkeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piel,</hi>
                     <pb n="140" facs="tcp:199150:72"/>were ſurrendered to the <hi>French,</hi> after the Battle. The Army had orders to march towards <hi>Hailbron,</hi> but the Duke fell dangerouſly ſick; ſo that he was forced to withdraw, and be carried to <hi>Philipsbourgh.</hi> At this time, the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all its Forces under two Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, the Archduke <hi>Leopold,</hi> and General <hi>Galaz.</hi> There were in this Army above Thirty thouſand Men. Monſieur <hi>de Turenne,</hi> and the Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal of <hi>Grammont,</hi> commanded in the <hi>French</hi> Army, inſtead of the Duke <hi>d'Enguien;</hi> they had not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Twelve or thirteen thouſand Men, yet they behaved themſelves ſo gallantly, that the Imperialiſts could never come to fight them. They retreated with their Soldiers through their Enemies Countrey, and returned ſafe home into the Borders of <hi>France.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> Generals were highly commended for their Wiſdom, in foreſeeing the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:199150:72"/>danger of a General Battle; and for their care and prudence, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging the Retreat to ſave their Men.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Lorraine,</hi> the Mareſchal <hi>de Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leroy</hi> was ſent with an Army to drive the Duke out of his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, becauſe he had Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf with the Enemies of <hi>France.</hi> The Inhabitants are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally inclined to favor the <hi>French,</hi> therefore they made no great reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but ſubmitted themſelves to the King of <hi>Frances</hi> General, only <hi>La Mothe</hi> held out. Monſieur <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galoty</hi> undertook to defend it; but his death cauſed it to be ſurrendred alſo: So that the poor Duke was driven out of all his Patrimony, by the overruling power of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Catalonia,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> were no leſs ſucceſsful for the General, the Count <hi>du Pleſſis-Praſlin</hi> took <hi>Roſes</hi> the nineteenth of <hi>May,</hi> and the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:199150:73"/>Count <hi>de Harcourt,</hi> Viceroy of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talonia,</hi> defeated the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the Fields of <hi>Liorerys,</hi> and forced the Town of <hi>Balaguier</hi> to open its Gates. <hi>Du Pleſſis-Praſlin</hi> was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored with the Staff of a Mareſchal of <hi>France,</hi> for his good ſervice to that Crown; and was commanded into <hi>Italy</hi> to aſſiſt Prince <hi>Thomas</hi> againſt the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> In the Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Milan, Viguerano</hi> was taken from them; but when the Prince was in his Retreat, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals overpowered him; and had it not been for the ſeaſonable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of the new Mareſchal, his Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers had been cut in pieces, and totally routed.</p>
                  <p>The next year 1646. the War was managed with the ſame fury as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, eſpecially in <hi>Flanders,</hi> under the Dukes of <hi>Orleans</hi> and <hi>d'En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guien,</hi> who laid ſiege, with a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Army, well appointed, to the City of <hi>Courtray,</hi> which they took
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:199150:73"/>in the preſence of all the Forces of the Houſe of <hi>Austria,</hi> that came with a deſign to raiſe the Siege. <hi>Mardike</hi> was again retaken from the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and <hi>Dunkirk</hi> was beſieged by the Duke of <hi>Enguien. Caracena</hi> and <hi>Lambay</hi> were the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, but they did not dare to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture a pitcht Battle. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Leda,</hi> a famous and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Commander, was then Governor of this Town, that was well fortified by Nature as well as by Art. Nevertheleſs, the <hi>French</hi> won it in thirteen days, and forced the beſieged to a Capitulation. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, Prince <hi>Thomas,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Brezé</hi> beſieged, and took <hi>Orbiſelle;</hi> but the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were ſo ſtrong in <hi>Italy,</hi> that the Court or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Mareſchal <hi>de la Meilleray,</hi> and <hi>du Pleſſis-Praſlin,</hi> with United Forces to march thither; they took two ſmall places, <hi>Paombino</hi> and <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolongone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:199150:74"/>
                  <p>About this time, <hi>Henry de Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon,</hi> Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> died, the Six and twentieth of <hi>December,</hi> and his eldeſt Son, the Duke of <hi>Enguien</hi> ſucceeded him in his Principality, and to the honor of being the firſt Prince of the Blood Royal of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the year 1647. the Mareſchal <hi>de Gaſſion</hi> forced many places to ſubmit; he was wounded at the ſiege of <hi>Lens,</hi> and carried to <hi>Arras,</hi> where he died. Monſieur <hi>Villequier</hi> commanded in his abſence, and took the Town.</p>
                  <p>About this time the Duke of <hi>Brezé</hi> was killed over againſt <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> with a Cannon Bullet, and his Fleet was put to flight by the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Armado.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the misfortunes and ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> brought all his family to ruine. He had been ſollicited by the Rebellious <hi>Neapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litans,</hi> to command their Army
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:199150:74"/>againſt their lawful Prince. He too credulouſly truſted an unconſtant Rabble, and went to <hi>Naples</hi> to manage a War againſt <hi>Spain,</hi> in that part of the World, and diſpoſſeſs the Houſe of <hi>Austria,</hi> of one of its beſt Kingdoms.</p>
                  <p>His firſt arrival was attended by ſome Succeſſes, and the favor of the Inhabitants; but when the Court of <hi>France,</hi> out of a jealouſie of his greatneſs, began to frown upon him, and deny the aſſiſtance which they had promiſed, and might have ſent him; the <hi>Neapoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> betrayed him to their old Maſters for their own ſafety and pardon. He was carried into the Priſons of <hi>Spain,</hi> from whence he could ſcarce obtain his freedom in three years. This great diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment brought the Houſe of <hi>Guiſe</hi> to a low eſtate, together with ſome other miſcarriages, that they have been guilty of.</p>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:199150:75"/>
                  <p>In this Campagne, <hi>Lerida,</hi> the ſtrongeſt Bulwark upon the Borders of <hi>Spain,</hi> was ſtreightly beſieged by the Army of the Prince of <hi>Condé.</hi> The Count <hi>de Harcourt,</hi> had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted it the year before; but this place ſtood it out, till the laſt, ſo that the ſiege was raiſed to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cor ſome other more conſiderable Town, which the <hi>Spaniard</hi> was ready to carry.</p>
                  <p>In the beginning of the Spring 1648. that diſmal year for <hi>England,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> appeared again at the head of an Army in <hi>Flanders.</hi> where he took <hi>Ypres</hi> in twelve days; but before this ſiege was over, where the <hi>French</hi> Army ſuffered many wants, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered <hi>Funes, Courtray,</hi> and <hi>Lens.</hi> Theſe advantages had made them contemn their Enemies, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Prince: So that General <hi>Beck,</hi> aſſiſtant to the Arch duke <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pold</hi> in his Army, aſſured him of a
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:199150:75"/>full victory over the <hi>French.</hi> With this perſwaſion, they ventured to ingage, but the Troops of <hi>Lorraine</hi> were diſordered in the Battle, and the Archdukes Cavalry were ſo miſerably treated, that if the Prince <hi>de Ligny</hi> had not come in, with his reſerve, the Archduke had been made priſoner. General <hi>Beck</hi> died with the diſpleaſure of his ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, as well as by his wounds. This Battle was fought the twentieth of <hi>August;</hi> it cauſed ſeveral petty Towns to open their Gates, as <hi>Lens</hi> and <hi>Furnes, &amp;c.</hi> At this time, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchal <hi>de Schomberg,</hi> the Kings Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> took the Town of <hi>Tortoiſe,</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencia,</hi> and defeated the Army of <hi>Don Franciſco de Melo,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> General, that came to relieve it.</p>
                  <p>All theſe Sieges, Battles, and Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters, hapned during the Treaty at <hi>Munster,</hi> which excluded the <hi>French</hi> and the <hi>Spaniard.</hi> Their
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:199150:76"/>quarrels alone could not be ended, for the <hi>Spaniard</hi> had intelligence of a ſecret Conſpiracy in <hi>France,</hi> where the greateſt Princes were concerned. He did therefore expect to recover what he had loſt by the favor of the Domeſtick Wars, and troubles of his Neighbors. The Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> and many more of the Blood Royal were united together, they publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their <hi>Manifeſto</hi> to juſtifie their taking up Arms to reform the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as was pretended, and to remove the Cardinal from that great truſt repoſed in him by the Queen. <hi>Paris</hi> held for the Rebels, and many other Towns were in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of following the ſame example. The Inhabitants were more then uſually ſcurrilous and ſcandalous againſt the King, the Queen, and the Cardinal. Theſe troubles had almoſt deprived the young King of his Crown and Scepter, had it not been for the ſeaſonable aſſiſtance
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:199150:76"/>and kind Mediation of our great Monarch, and the vigorous endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors of the Mareſchal <hi>de Turenne,</hi> more faithful to his King then to his Religion.</p>
                  <p>At laſt after much Bloodſhed in an inteſtine War, the Prince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated into <hi>Flanders,</hi> with thoſe of his party, whom neither Love, Loyalty, nor Intereſt, could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade to guard their young King. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> put him at the Head of their Troops, with which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered almoſt all the Towns that he had formerly loſt. If the Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal <hi>de Turenne</hi> had not ſtopped the progreſs of the Princes victories, he had invaded the Crown it ſelf as well as the Frontier Towns. But after an abſence of ſeveral years, the King invited him home, received him into his favor, beſtowed upon him his Government, and Employs, and treated the Dukes of <hi>Conti,</hi> and <hi>Longueville,</hi> in the ſame generous
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:199150:77"/>manner, publiſhing a General Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to all other offenders in the Civil Wars.</p>
                  <p>On the Seventh of <hi>September,</hi> 1651. the King being thirteen years old, was declared of Age, ſufficient to take upon him the Government, and to begin to act in perſon, in that ſphere where providence had put him. The Declaration was approved of in the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> and proclaimed all over the Land.</p>
                  <p>The War continued ſtill between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi> In the years 49, 50, 51, and 52, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> had the greateſt Succeſſes againſt the <hi>French;</hi> for they were aſſiſted by the Sedition and Treachery of the Inhabitants, as much as by their own valor and numbers of Men, to recover more then they had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſt. But after the Kings majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, he appeared himſelf at the head of his Troops, and, with his preſence, gave them ſo much cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:199150:77"/>and reſolution, that they turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the fortune of War. The City of <hi>Bar,</hi> and the Caſtle of <hi>Ligny,</hi> was ſurrendred to the Mareſchal <hi>de la Ferté,</hi> in 1653. The Duke of <hi>Eſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> beſieged <hi>Bellegard,</hi> but could not take it, till the news was come, that the King was in the Camp; then the Governor was loath to ſtand it out againſt his own Prince. <hi>Rethel</hi> and <hi>Mouzon</hi> were retaken by Monſieur <hi>Turenne, St. Menehou</hi> by <hi>la Ferté,</hi> the twenty ſeventh of <hi>November. Du Pleſſis Praſlin</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved himſelf ſo gallantly in taking this place, that the King gave it him to command. <hi>Grancey</hi> ſurpriſed <hi>Castillon,</hi> and withſtood the valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous efforts of General <hi>Caracena.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The year 1654. was honored with the greateſt ſolemnity, and moſt ſacred Ceremony of <hi>France,</hi> the Coronation of their King at <hi>Rheims,</hi> with that holy Oyl which they affirm to be faln from Heaven,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:199150:78"/>and ſent from God for that purpoſe, to anoint their Kings therewith. When they have been thus inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, the people have a particular reſpect for their perſons.</p>
                  <p>After this, <hi>Stenay</hi> was beſieged by the <hi>French,</hi> commanded by Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal <hi>d' Hocquincourt;</hi> when the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard</hi> ſaw they could not hinder the taking of this place, they labored to make a Diverſion, and to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence themſelves for their loſs, by the invaſion of <hi>Arras. Turenne, la Ferté,</hi> and <hi>Hocquincourt,</hi> had orders to hazard all, rather then to ſuffer this great City to fall into their hands. When they had called a Council of War, they reſolved to attack the Lines and Trenches, which they did with much reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the night, the 24 and 25 days of <hi>August. Hocquincourt</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered firſt into the Enemies Camp, through the Troops of the Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> but he was beaten back
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:199150:78"/>with a great ſlaughter of his Men; the other Commanders relieved, and ſeconded him: So that at laſt the <hi>Spaniard</hi> was forced to leave his Trenches with ſome loſs of Men, of Ammunition, and Baggage: For the Governor of the Town ſallied out at the ſame time, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo much aſſiſtance, that the Enemy deſpaired of being able to gain the Walls. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral preſerved his Army by a ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able retreat, which was managed with that prudence and courage, that he hath worthily deſerved the admiration of his Enemies. The King went to viſit his Camp and Army immediately after this Siege was raiſed, to encourage and reward his brave Soldiers.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Catalonia</hi> alſo, the Prince of <hi>Conti</hi> had ſome ſucceſs in taking <hi>Conflans</hi> and <hi>Cerdagne</hi> from the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard.</hi> About the beginning of the Spring 1655. <hi>Landrecy, Maubeuge,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:199150:79"/>Condé,</hi> and <hi>St. Guilham,</hi> ſubmitted themſelves again to the <hi>French</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy. Thus theſe ſmall places were often taken and retaken by the Armies of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France.</hi> At every advantage, in the Field, theſe weaker Towns, of no reſiſtance, were forced, for their preſervation, to prefer their Safety to their Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to ſide with the ſtrongeſt party.</p>
                  <p>In this year there was a League Offenſive and Defenſive, made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Cromwel</hi> and <hi>Mazarin,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Spain,</hi> upon conditions diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graceful to the King and Court of <hi>France.</hi> Monſieur <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited his Maſters Affairs ſo notably, that he got that Arch-Rebel to ſend over, in the beginning of the Spring 1656. an Army of ſtout Soldiers, commanded by <hi>Reynolds.</hi> For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>France</hi> abounds in Men, it is wont to make uſe of the valor of its Neighbors, in all Wars, againſt
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:199150:79"/>ſtrangers: For it hath been found, by experience, that the <hi>French</hi> are good for the firſt Onſet, but cannot abide nor weather ſo many diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as the <hi>Engliſh, Scotch,</hi> and <hi>Switzers</hi> can in War; beſides their Foot are not to be compared to ours. Therefore they may aſcribe their moſt difficult Conqueſts to their Money, and to the <hi>Engliſh, Scotch, Iriſh,</hi> and <hi>Switzers</hi> valor; as we ſhall ſee in ſeveral late Encount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and <hi>Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The year 1656. was noted for the remarkable Siege of <hi>Valancien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> where the <hi>French</hi> received an overthrow, and were forced to quit the place; but afterwards they took <hi>Cappelle</hi> and <hi>Valencia</hi> in <hi>Italy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the beginning of the Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne 1657. <hi>Montmedy</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged by <hi>la Ferté,</hi> the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf went thither, after that the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors which were intended for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:199150:80"/>were happily routed. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the City yielded to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and opened its Gates to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him on the ſeventh of <hi>Auguſt. St. Venant, Bourbourg,</hi> and the Fort of <hi>Mardike,</hi> alſo were taken by <hi>Turenne.</hi> Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſerved him in good ſtead in the recovering of theſe places, eſpecially in ſtorming of <hi>Mardike.</hi> The attempt was not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed feaſable by the <hi>French</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, who had a deſign rather to beſiege it, then to win it by an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault. But our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Commanders undertook this perillous attempt, Sir <hi>Tho. Morgan,</hi> now Governor of <hi>Jerſey,</hi> lead his Party with ſo much courage and reſolution, that they recovered the top of the Walls in an inſtant, paſſing through ſhowers of ſhot and fire, to the great aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the reſt of the Army. This Gentleman hath purchaſed to himſelf the name and honor of one of the braveſt Soldiers of <hi>Europe.</hi>
                     <pb n="157" facs="tcp:199150:80"/>And when the <hi>Spaniard</hi> ventured in the night to ſurpriſe this Fort again, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſaved it, beat back the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and obliged them to a ſpeedy retreat to <hi>Dunkirk.</hi> After this <hi>Turenne</hi> was employed with a Flying Party to raiſe the Siege of <hi>Ardres,</hi> which he did with ſo much bravery, that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> received there a conſiderable loſs.</p>
                  <p>But all theſe Conqueſts were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable to thoſe of the next year 1658. <hi>Turenne</hi> and <hi>La Ferté</hi> were the two Generals of the <hi>French,</hi> and after the death of <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds,</hi> drowned near <hi>Goodwin Sands,</hi> in a ſmall Boat in which he ventured to paſs from <hi>Mardike</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> my Lord <hi>Lockart,</hi> then Ambaſſador at <hi>Paris,</hi> took the charge of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces. The Army was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to beſiege <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> for it had been agreed between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> that this place ſhould be put into the <hi>Engliſh</hi> hands. It
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:199150:81"/>was ſurrounded the Twenty fifth of <hi>May;</hi> which when the Marqueſs of <hi>Leda</hi> had notice of, he ſhut himſelf in, with a ſtrong Garriſon, reſolving to defend it, or die there. The Siege was carried on very reſolutely, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Armies made their approaches on a ſudden; ſo that the fear of looſing this ſtrong place, cauſed the Archduke to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor to raiſe the Siege by aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in their Trenches. <hi>Turenne</hi> confided in his own ſtrength, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he heard of the Enemies approach, he marched bravely out of his Camp to meet the Archduke, the victory declared for the <hi>French.</hi> In this encounter, it was the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to fight with their own Countrey-men. In the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army, the Noble and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious Duke of <hi>York,</hi> a Prince of an invincible reſolution, was enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the <hi>Spaniard</hi> as one of the beſt Commanders of that Army.
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:199150:81"/>That wiſe Nation, as well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Men as in Affairs, would not ſuffer ſo great a Courage idle, in time of War. If I might have the liberty in this ſuccinct Narration, I could give an account of the moſt heroick actions of his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; inſomuch, that <hi>Turenne,</hi> and the other Generals, have often con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed him to be the ableſt and moſt skilful Commander of the World. His Courage and Wiſdom had not that ſucceſs that could have been expected at this time; for the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Regiments under my Lord <hi>Lockart,</hi> eſpecially that of Colonel <hi>Alſop,</hi> beat back the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and purſued them over the Sandy Hills, with a great ſlaughter. This victory was due cheifly to the courage of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the fifteenth of <hi>June,</hi> 1658. After the Retreat of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Army returned to the Siege, where the Marqueſs of <hi>Leda</hi> was killed with a Bullet. After
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:199150:82"/>his death the Town began to liſten to terms of Surrendring, which were agreed on the Two and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of <hi>June.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The King entered into the City, to take poſſeſſion of it, afterwards he delivered it up to my Lord <hi>Lockart,</hi> for the uſe of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> whoſe Blood and Valor had got it from the Enemy. <hi>Bergues, Furnes,</hi> and <hi>Dixmuyde,</hi> yielded alſo to the Kings Summons, ſo did <hi>Oudenard. Ypres</hi> ſtaid for a Siege, and when the Prince of <hi>Ligny</hi> had gathered the Relicks of the Diſperſed Army, beaten before <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> he labored to raiſe it; but was beaten off with loſs by <hi>Turenne,</hi> who took after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Menein,</hi> and many other ſmall Caſtles.</p>
                  <p>At that time <hi>La Ferté</hi> aſſaulted <hi>Gravelin,</hi> but could not recover it in a Moneth, for the Garriſon was ſtrong and reſolute. Many brave Actions hapned in this attempt, the
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:199150:82"/>beſiegers and beſieged, behaved themſelves very gallantly; at laſt they capitulated upon honorable terms, the Eight and twentieth of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the interim, the Dukes of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dena</hi> and <hi>Navailes,</hi> took <hi>Mortera</hi> for the <hi>French.</hi> This firſt hath always been devoted to the Crown of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Spaniard</hi> endeavored to take from the <hi>French,</hi> ſome little places which they recovered; but it is certain, that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> was the greater looſer. Therefore the Princes of the Empire aſſembled, together to conſult about the chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of another Emperor at <hi>Franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> ſent to deſire his Majeſty of <hi>France,</hi> to hearken to an Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. The King of <hi>Spain, Philip</hi> the Fourth, had cauſed ſome Overtures of Peace to be made by the Popes Mediation. The <hi>French</hi> Court entertained them wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:199150:83"/>upon condition of a match, between the young King, and the <hi>Infanta of Spain.</hi> When the King was at <hi>Lions,</hi> an Envoy came to him from <hi>Madrid,</hi> about this Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Cardinal had orders to have a private Conference with him, to make way for the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors <hi>de Lionne</hi> and <hi>Pimentel.</hi> The firſt was diſpatched away to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> the ſecond went to <hi>Paris.</hi> They dealt ſo effectually, that all Differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences were compoſed, Articles were concluded, and the great breach was made up, to the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both Princes and Kingdoms. The Queen-Mother was not a little uſeful in this buſineſs; for when the Cardinal did ſeem to put in ſome Demurs, ſhe declared, That the Peace ſhould be made without him, for that ſhe was reſolved, that her Son ſhould match with one of her own Kinred.</p>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:199150:83"/>
                  <p>The Kings indiſpoſition had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ruined this Affair, for he fell dangerouſly ſick; but he recovered after a few days diſtemper. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he made a progreſs into the fartheſt confines of his Kingdom; for there had been ſome diſcontents and diſorders about <hi>Lions, Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> and <hi>Provence,</hi> which could not be terminated without his coming. When he was at <hi>Lions,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> came to wait upon him. This Prince is ſo near a Neighbor to <hi>France,</hi> that he is forced to keep his friendſhip, for fear of looſing his Principality; which hath been ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times in great danger to be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up, by this great Monarch, at the leaſt diſtaſte.</p>
                  <p>In the mean time, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity was very ſlow in concluding the Peace; that Court trifled away the time in Conſultations and Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, whileſt the Spring of the next year 1659. was coming on apace.
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:199150:84"/>Which cauſed the King to give or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for new levies of Soldiers, to appoint Generals and Commanders, as if he had intended to proſecute the War as vigorouſly as before. This made the <hi>Spaniard</hi> deſire a Truce of four Moneths; from the eighth of <hi>March,</hi> to the third of <hi>July,</hi> which was granted the King, That it ſhould continue till his Declaration to the contrary or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
                  <p>In order to a Peace, <hi>Mazarin</hi> went to <hi>Bayonne,</hi> and <hi>Don Louïs d' Aro de Guſman</hi> came to S. <hi>Sebaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> to treat more commodiouſly. Theſe two Plenipotentiaries at laſt concluded and ſigned the Articles the ſeventh of <hi>November</hi> next enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The Inhabitants of S. <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> of S. <hi>John de Luz,</hi> and of the Neighboring Cities declared their ſatisfaction and joy, by Bonefires, and other publick ſigns.</p>
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:199150:84"/>
                  <p>Whilſt the buſineſs was in debate, the <hi>French</hi> Court was at <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> and <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> that it might be ſooner conſulted in all difficult Matters. After the concluſion of the Treaty, the <hi>French</hi> King ſent a Procuration to <hi>Don Louïs d' Aro,</hi> to eſpouſe the <hi>Infanta of Spain</hi> in his name. The Marriage was performed in <hi>Fonta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabia</hi> in the preſence of the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> the third day of <hi>June.</hi> The two Kings met in the <hi>Iſle of Conference,</hi> ſcituate between both Kingdoms, where the young Queen was delivered to her Husband, and both Kings ſwore to keep, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to one another the Treaty of Peace.</p>
                  <p>After this interview, they ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; the <hi>French</hi> King and Queen was received at S. <hi>John de Luz,</hi> with much pomp and Joy; and in their journey to <hi>Paris,</hi> every good City in their way expreſſed their extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary ſatisfaction, for the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:199150:85"/>and Peace between the two Kingdoms. But their Reception at <hi>Paris,</hi> was one of the moſt glorious Ceremonies, the moſt ſplendid Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of our Age. The young Queen was carried in an open Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, ſhining with all the riches of the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West Indies;</hi> ſhe was attended upon by the whole Court, in their greateſt ſplendor and glory. The People, the Clergy, and the Nobility, did welcome her with ſuch expreſſions of joy, that they are not credible.</p>
                  <p>In the beginning of the next year 1661. on the nineth of <hi>March,</hi> the great Miniſter of State, Cardinal <hi>Mazarin,</hi> paid his laſt debt to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> having, by his policy, raiſed himſelf and family from a low be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, to the greateſt honors in <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Court was pleaſed to Mourn for him, but they quickly caſt off their ſad attire, when Monſieur of
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:199150:85"/>
                     <hi>France</hi> reſolved to marry with the Princeſs of <hi>England:</hi> A Lady, very well accompliſhed in <hi>Beauty</hi> and <hi>Vertue.</hi> The publick ceremony was performed on the One and thirtieth of <hi>March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There hapned nothing remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able this year, till the latter end. The firſt day of <hi>November,</hi> the <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin</hi> of <hi>France</hi> was born, to the great joy of all that Kingdom, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Montauſier</hi> was appointed to be his Governor.</p>
                  <p>One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty and two, the King made Seventy two Knights of the Order of the <hi>S. Eſprit;</hi> all Perſons of the greateſt Nobility, and approved valor. In the ſame year there hapned a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between the Ambaſſadors of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> about preceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, in the City of <hi>London.</hi> The <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> were prepared to receive the <hi>French;</hi> ſo that the tumult was great, and ſome Bloodſhed on both ſides.</p>
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:199150:86"/>
                  <p>The <hi>French</hi> ſent their Complaints to <hi>Madrid,</hi> the King gave them ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and forbad all his Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors for the future, to appear in any publick ſolemnity with the Ambaſſadors of <hi>France;</hi> for they claim a precedency in all Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> unleſs it be in <hi>Vienna,</hi> where the Houſe of <hi>Austria</hi> are Lords. The King of <hi>Spain</hi> preferred in this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the Peace and Quiet of his Kingdoms to this odd <hi>Punctilio</hi> of Honor.</p>
                  <p>This year was ſpent in Sports and publick Divertiſements of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Nobility at court, till the Moneth of <hi>November.</hi> Then the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador in <hi>England,</hi> had Orders to demand the reſtitution of <hi>Dunkirk</hi> to the <hi>French,</hi> for a ſum of Money, according to their pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Agreement with <hi>Cromwel.</hi> It was generally ſuppoſed by the wiſeſt in <hi>France,</hi> that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> would never part with a place ſo well fortified,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:199150:86"/>by their late induſtry, purchaſed with the Blood of many of their braveſt Men that took it, and ſo handy and commodious to them, both in Peace and War; and that therefore there would be a diſpute between the two Nations, for the recovery of it. But it hapned other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to the Univerſal Sorrow of all our people, <hi>Dunkirke</hi> was ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and the <hi>French</hi> King made his entry into it the ſecond day of <hi>December.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There had been a Treaty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the old Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> and this young King, by which the Duke made over to him, all his Right, Title, and Intereſt, in the Dutchy of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> for ſome Lands in lieu of it; and for the priviledge of being declared Heir to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> in caſe the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Bourbon</hi> did fail. This A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement had been made the ſixth of <hi>February,</hi> 1662. and confirmed
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:199150:87"/>in the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> in the Moneth of <hi>March.</hi> So that the <hi>French</hi> ſeiſed upon all the Cities and Countrey of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> only the ſtrong Town of <hi>Marſal</hi> remained in the Dukes hands, who ſeemed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to deliver it. Beſides the young Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> was ſuppoſed to have won the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers there in Garriſon, therefore they would not ſurrender it upon Summons.</p>
                  <p>This affair cauſed the King to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel into that Countrey, with a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Army, to reduce it to his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, commanding that <hi>Marſal</hi> ſhould be beſieged without delay. His ſudden motion ſurpriſed the Duke, and found him unprovided; therefore he went to meet his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty at <hi>Metz</hi> in <hi>Lorraine,</hi> to ſubmit himſelf unto him. The King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him very generouſly, and made him welcome; <hi>Marſal,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Agreement, was put into
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:199150:87"/>the <hi>French</hi> hands, on the third of <hi>September,</hi> 1663.</p>
                  <p>A little before, the <hi>French</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador Monſieur <hi>de Crequi,</hi> had been affronted, and in danger of his perſon, in the City of <hi>Rome.</hi> Some of the Popes Guards ſhot into his Coach, and wounded his ſervants. When the Court of <hi>France</hi> heard of it, the King commanded the Popes <hi>Nuncio,</hi> then at <hi>Paris,</hi> to depart out of the Kingdom, and ſent for his Generals, ordering them to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for a War. <hi>Alexander</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth did then ſit in S. <hi>Peters</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Chair. He ſent immediately, upon the news of the coming of the <hi>French</hi> Army, an Expreſs, to aſſure his Majeſty, that he was much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied with the deed, and that he would give him all the ſatisfaction that he ſhould deſire. The City of <hi>Piſa</hi> was pitched upon to examine and diſcourſe of this affair, where the Popes, and the <hi>French</hi> Deputies,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:199150:88"/>concluded it the Twelfth of <hi>March,</hi> 1664. to the great joy of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Catholicks. The Pope yielded to his own diſhonor, that his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew <hi>Flavio Chigi</hi> ſhould wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the King, and beg his pardon, that a Monument ſhould be erected in the very place, for poſterity to gaze upon, with an Inſcription, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the cauſe of its ſtanding there. This was performed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly; but the zeal of the <hi>French,</hi> for their King, and their concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his honor, is very remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in this occaſion. The Parliament of <hi>Aix</hi> hearing of the affront given to the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador, and the Kings reſolution to revenge it, made ſome levies of Men of their own accord, and marched to <hi>Avignon,</hi> where they drive out the Garriſon, they ſurpriſed <hi>Carpentras,</hi> and all the Popes Territories near them. This action gave the King and Court great ſatisfaction, and facilitated an
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:199150:88"/>Agreement between him and the Pope; for the <hi>French</hi> are not ſo wedded to their Superſtitions, as to be ſo much afraid of the Popes thunderbolts as in former ages. It would become the wiſdom of the Politicians of this Nation, to ſhake off the Popes burdenſome Fetters, and eſtabliſh a Patriarch of their own. There wants nothing elſe to make their King an abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. Some of the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> have attempted to perſwade their Clergy to it, I hope God will one day open their eyes, to perceive their ſlavery to S. <hi>Peters</hi> counterfeit Keys, and to oblige them to uſe that liberty unto which Providence invites them.</p>
                  <p>At the ſame time, that the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal was in <hi>France,</hi> the Emperor deſired the Kings Succors, to help him againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> who had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded his Dominions. This motion pleaſed the <hi>French</hi> humor, for they
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:199150:89"/>would be thought to be the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions of Chriſtianity againſt the Infidels. The King ordered, as ſome ſay, about Ten thouſand Men to march under the command of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Coligny,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>de la Fueillade,</hi> who is now Duke of <hi>Roannez.</hi> This Army joyned with the Imperialiſts about the Moneth of <hi>June,</hi> 1665. they found out the <hi>Turks</hi> Army, and encountered with them twice. It is certain, the <hi>French</hi> behaved themſelves very gallantly in this expedition; ſo that the Enemies were worſted, and in their retreat, over the River of <hi>Raab,</hi> they loſt about Five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men that were ſlain, Sixteen pieces of Cannon, and about One hundred and fifty Colours were taken, with much of their Baggage. The reſt of their Army fled, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to withſtand the Chriſtians valor.</p>
                  <pb n="175" facs="tcp:199150:89"/>
                  <p>The Queen-Mother of <hi>France</hi> fell dangerouſly ſick, and died the Twentieth of <hi>January,</hi> in that omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous year One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty ſix. She was much lamented in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> for ſhe was an excellent Princeſs.</p>
                  <p>At this time there was War be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and the States of <hi>Holland.</hi> Their Fleets had had a bruſh at Sea, where the brave Duke of <hi>York</hi> adventured, in perſon, againſt their Squadrons, more in number then ours. <hi>Opdam</hi> their Admiral was blown up, and after a ſharp fight they fled to their own Coaſt, to carry thither the ſad news of their defeat, and of the loſs of many Ships taken by the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> When the <hi>French</hi> ſaw that the <hi>Hollander</hi> was likely to be worſted, he pretended an obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to defend them; therefore he declared War againſt us, not ſo much with an intention to aſſiſt the
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:199150:90"/>
                     <hi>Hollander</hi> by Sea, as to ſtand by with his Fleet, and judge of the blows. However, the countenance of ſuch a Prince, dreadful to all the World, becauſe it was not known yet what miſcheif he could do, helped them very much.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>French</hi> made no attempts upon us at home, unleſs it be upon our induſtrious Merchants, who loſt ſome Goods and Ships at Sea. But in the <hi>West Indies</hi> their treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and cruelty were remarkable in the Iland of S. <hi>Chriſtophers,</hi> where the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Plantations had lived in Peace and Amity ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral years, they ſuppoſed our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> would endeavor to drive them away, after this breach between the two Nations. To prevent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which the others had no deſign to execute, they fell upon them unawares, and maſſacred their Neighbors, to their eternal ſhame, plundering all their Goods, and
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:199150:90"/>rifling their habitations. They ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed next, the Iſlands of <hi>Antego, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bago,</hi> and S. <hi>Euſtache.</hi> Our Men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to revenge theſe outrages up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe of <hi>Guadeloupe;</hi> but the Fleet that ſet forth for that intent, was diſperſed by a terrible <hi>Hurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane,</hi> and ſome of our Ships were broken and ſhipwracked, amongſt the <hi>American</hi> Iſlands, to the great diſappointment of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> This War between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> continued till the year 1668. the Peace was concluded at <hi>Breda;</hi> for the <hi>French</hi> had no quarrel with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but only as was pretended in defence of <hi>Holland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The truth is, the King did not care to have two Enemies upon his back, at once; he was reſolved to take into his poſſeſſion ſome Towns in <hi>Flanders,</hi> belonging to the Crown of <hi>Spain;</hi> he was glad that His Majeſty of <hi>England,</hi> would let him alone, and not intermeddle in this
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:199150:91"/>Affair. The pretence to colour the invaſion was, that ſome Articles of the Treaty of Marriage were not performed by the Court of <hi>Spain.</hi> The King, by his Ambaſſador at <hi>Madrid,</hi> acquainted them with his demands, but they neglected to give him ſatisfaction; this cauſed him to publiſh his <hi>Manifeſto,</hi> to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſeiſure of thoſe Lands and Towns which, he ſaid, belonged to the Queen, by agreement at her Marriage.</p>
                  <p>At the end of <hi>May,</hi> 1667. he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into <hi>Flanders</hi> with about Thirty thouſand Men, well furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The firſt Garriſons were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, as <hi>Armantiers, La Baſſée, Condé,</hi> and <hi>S. Guilhain. Bergnes</hi> and <hi>Furnes,</hi> were yielded up to the Mareſchal d' <hi>Aumont.</hi> The King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Charleroy</hi> to be rebuilt and fortified, that it might ſerve as a Bulwark againſt <hi>Flanders. Tournay</hi> was beſieged and aſſaulted, but
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:199150:91"/>could not ſtop the impetuous tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of the <hi>French,</hi> that carried, at this time, all before them. <hi>Douay</hi> waited for their coming, its Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor had the meen to ſtop the <hi>French</hi> progreſs: But upon his Majeſties Summons, he obeyed, and ſent him the Keys. <hi>Courtray</hi> was taken in four days; <hi>Oudenard</hi> and <hi>Alost</hi> were quickly frighted into a compliance with the <hi>French. Lille</hi> was the next Garriſon that had the unhappineſs to be in the <hi>French</hi> Kings way. The Governor of this place had the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of a brave Commander, he had under him 800 Horſe and 4000 Foot in Garriſon, and was reſolved to defend it. Therefore the King came before it with his whole Army, laid ſiege to it, and, after a very ſtout reſiſtance, obliged the renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Governor to ſave the reſt of his men by yielding up the Town, upon honorable terms. The King made his entry on the Eight and
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:199150:92"/>twentieth day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred ſixty and ſeven.</p>
                  <p>During the ſiege, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Commanders had raiſed a ſmall Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, with an intent to Aſſault the <hi>French</hi> before <hi>Lille. Marcin</hi> was at the Head of theſe Troops in his march, when <hi>Crequy, Rouvray, Lille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonne,</hi> and <hi>Bellefonds,</hi> met with his Cavalry, in two ſeveral Rencoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and broke his deſign. For theſe Captains had ſo diſordered his Men, and ſcared them, that they could not be perſwaded to attempt upon the <hi>French</hi> again without more aſſiſtance.</p>
                  <p>After this Campagne, the King went to <hi>Paris,</hi> and in the firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Spring, One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred ſixty and eight, he gave order to his Armies to march towards the <hi>Franche Comte.</hi> The Prince had the command of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition; but when the Inhabitants underſtood it, they ſent to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:199150:92"/>Deputies, to treat of yielding to him, to prevent the ſpoils of an Army. Whileſt the Deputies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed, the Prince, with his Army, being ready, went ſtreight to <hi>Beſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon,</hi> where he encamped. On the ſixth of <hi>February,</hi> it was ſurrendered into his hands; ſome other Towns were taken without reſiſtance, and <hi>Salines</hi> was ſeiſed upon ſuddenly. At that time his Majeſty was come to his Army, which he cauſed to draw near to <hi>Dole,</hi> a place well for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified and furniſhed with Men and Cannon, which cauſed the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants to ſtand upon their Guards, and think of a reſiſtance; but when they ſaw that the <hi>French</hi> had poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed all the Outworks in one night, and lodged themſelves under their Counterſcarpe, they accepted of his Majeſties offers, and ſent him the Keys of their City.</p>
                  <p>All theſe places were taken in twelve days, to the great aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:199150:93"/>of all Neighboring People.</p>
                  <p>There had been ſome overtures of Peace made the year before: To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the concluſion of them, the King appeared with his Army this year ſo early in the Field; for the <hi>Dutch</hi> had threatned him, by their Ambaſſador, to joyn with the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard,</hi> if he would not hearken to an accommodation. This Speech, together with the Reſolution of his Neighbors, of riſing up in Arms againſt him, brought forth the Treaty of <hi>Aix la Chappelle:</hi> Unto which place, <hi>Colbert</hi> was ſent as an Extraordinary Ambaſſador, to meet with the Miniſters of the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Princes. It was ſigned the ſixth of <hi>May,</hi> and ſent to be publiſhed at <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Bruſſels;</hi> but the <hi>French</hi> King was mightily offended at the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who had forced him, againſt his will, to this concluſion of Peace; therefore in due time he was reſolved to find an occaſion
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:199150:93"/>to puniſh them for their ſauci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  <p>In the mean while, the Nobility and Gallants of <hi>France</hi> that had prepared their equipages, for the next Campagne, when they ſaw themſelves diſappointed by a haſty Peace, reſolved to venture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in Foreign ſervice. <hi>Fame</hi> had told them of the long Siege of <hi>Candy,</hi> by the <hi>Turks,</hi> and that theſe Infidels did daily win upon the beſieged by their numbers; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the greateſt Zealots of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to hazard their perſons for the releif of that noble City be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Venetians.</hi> The Duke <hi>de Roannez,</hi> the Count of <hi>St. Paul,</hi> the Duke <hi>de Chateau-Thierry,</hi> the Chevalier <hi>de Harcour,</hi> with many other brave Adventurers, voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ingaged themſelves in this expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. It is certain, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved themſelves with all the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry that could be expected. At
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:199150:94"/>their return, they acquainted the King with the condition of the place, and the ſtrength of the <hi>Turks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This perſwaded his Majeſty, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Sollicitations of the <hi>Venetians,</hi> to ſend over thither the Dukes of <hi>Beaufort</hi> and <hi>Navailles,</hi> with about 10000 Men, to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they could raiſe the ſiege. All the World expected a Succeſs an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the <hi>French</hi> courage: At their firſt ſallying out upon the <hi>Turks,</hi> they beat all down before them; but when the <hi>Turks</hi> ſaw their vigor abate, they charged furiouſly upon them, and routed them, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing them back into the City Walls. <hi>Beaufort</hi> himſelf was loſt, and kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as it is ſuppoſed, in the rout, but his body could not be found afterwards.</p>
                  <p>He was much to be blamed for venturing his perſon, and the honor of his Prince, amongſt the meaneſt
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:199150:94"/>Soldiers; for Commanders of his rank and quality, are to be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that the ſafety of the whole Army depends upon the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their lives: They are never to hazard themſelves in the Front of a Battle, but when their preſence is neceſſary, to give courage to their fainting Soldiers, or to add more vigor to them, when the victory is almoſt in their hands. After the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat of the <hi>French,</hi> the beſieged City was yielded up to the <hi>Turks</hi> General, upon very favorable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
                  <p>The King had intelligence about the end of the year 1669. that the Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> did endeavor to ſtir up the Emperor and King of <hi>Spain,</hi> againſt him. This cauſed him to ſend the Mareſchal <hi>de Crequy</hi> with an Army of 18000 Men into <hi>Lorraine,</hi> to take in that Countrey. The Duke ſeiſed upon <hi>Pont a Mouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and pulled down the Walls.
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:199150:95"/>
                     <hi>Epinal</hi> and <hi>Chaté</hi> held out a litteè, but they were, at laſt, Surrendered up into his hands, and the old Duke was driven out of all his Principality.</p>
                  <p>This year 1670. the King viſited his new conquered Towns in the <hi>Low Countreys,</hi> repairèd their breaches, reſtored their Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and put them all into a good poſture of defence. But that which was remarkable in this progreſs, the King had no extraordinary <hi>Militia;</hi> he truſted ſo much theſe new Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, that he entered into all their populous Towns, attended only by his houſhold Servants, and uſual Guards.</p>
                  <p>This got him the love and reſpect of the <hi>Walloons,</hi> and ſecured him the hearts of his people, as well as the Walls of their Towns.</p>
                  <p>About this time, a King of <hi>Guinny,</hi> who lives at a City called <hi>Arda,</hi> ſent an Ambaſſador to <hi>Paris</hi> to treat
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:199150:95"/>about an eſtabliſhment of a Trade, between that place, and the Iſlands of <hi>America,</hi> under the <hi>French</hi> Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The King entertained him, and his motion, very kindly, and ſent him back with Tokens of his liberality.</p>
                  <p>There had been an Order of the Kings Council publiſhed, by which certain Wares of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were prohibited in <hi>France.</hi> They labored, by their Ambaſſador, to perſwade the King to revoke this Order; but in vain, for the King was now reſolved to revenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon them, for their inſolent carriage towards him, and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in the <hi>West</hi> and <hi>East Indies,</hi> and in many Foreign Countreys; where they had ingroſſed all the Trade to themſelves.</p>
                  <p>It is certain, that both the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> had great cauſe to complain of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> who had, on ſeveral occaſions, diſcovered
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:199150:96"/>an unſufferable Pride, and a haugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty carriage, not to be endured by Crowned Heads. They had exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed their cruelty upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of both Kingdoms beyond the Seas, and had ſeiſed upon their Goods, affronting thereby their Princes who are ingaged to protect them.</p>
                  <p>Theſe, and other unjuſt practiſes, as was pretended, obliged the <hi>French</hi> to prepare for War: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in his Progreſs in <hi>Flanders,</hi> he viſited, himſelf, the Fortifications of all his Frontier Towns, and cauſed the weakeſt places to be fortified with new Works; from <hi>Dunkirke,</hi> he went to <hi>Amantiers,</hi> from thence to <hi>Lille,</hi> to <hi>Courtray,</hi> to <hi>Aeth.</hi> He found that Monſieur <hi>de Montal</hi> had ſtrongly repaired the Walls of <hi>Charle le Roy;</hi> for which, he highly commended him.</p>
                  <p>Before the War was proclaimed, Madam <hi>de Orleans,</hi> the only Siſter a
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:199150:96"/>live, of our Gracious Monarch, came over here unto <hi>England,</hi> to viſit the King, and the Duke of <hi>York.</hi> She was received with all the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of kindneſs, that <hi>Nature</hi> did require, and her Vertues de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. But as all our ſatisfactions are momentary, ſhe had no ſooner ſeen theſe dear Relations, but was forced to leave them again, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn over to <hi>France,</hi> where ſhe died ſo ſuddenly, that moſt men en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained the bad reports that were raiſed about her death. However, the Court of <hi>France</hi> honored her Birth and Vertues, with an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Mourning, and the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi>'s countenance ſeemed to be very ſad and penſive, until the King had cheared him up with the thoughts of another Wife. The Daughter of the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine</hi> was pitched upon; the Mareſchal <hi>du Pleſſis</hi> was ſent to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſe her in the Dukes name, in the
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:199150:97"/>City of <hi>Mets,</hi> the ſixteenth day of <hi>November.</hi> The Duke himſelf wen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as far as <hi>Chalons,</hi> to receive and welcome her: The King, the Queen, and all the Court expreſſed their joy and ſatisfaction for her ſafe arrival; and about a year after, ſhe was brought to Bed of a Son.</p>
                  <p>All this while, the War was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring againſt <hi>Holland. England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> were to unite their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by Sea and Land. On the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day of <hi>April,</hi> 1672. the King publiſhed his Declaration, to forbid all Commerce and Trade with the States of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces;</hi> and immediately after, appeared at the Head of an Army of One hundred and fifty thouſand Men, with whom he carried all before him in the <hi>Low Countreys,</hi> as a violent torrent: No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was of a ſufficient reſiſtance for ſo great a power; every one did judge, that he would win all the other Towns, the following Spring,
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:199150:97"/>if there were not a ſtop put to his undertakings. But the motion of the <hi>French</hi> is always violent at the firſt, and then at the leaſt diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it begins to abate. The Dutchy of <hi>Cleves,</hi> the Electorate of <hi>Cullen,</hi> the Dutchy of <hi>Limburgh,</hi> the County of <hi>Zutphen, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> and its Territories. <hi>Holland, Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, Overiſſell,</hi> the <hi>Oriental Frieze, Groningen,</hi> and the Dutchy of <hi>Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres,</hi> were full of <hi>French</hi> Troops, on a ſudden. <hi>Orſoy, Veſel, Burick,</hi> and <hi>Rhineburgh,</hi> that had been ſo ſtrongly Garriſoned, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> thought them to be the Bulwarks of their Land, were ſurrendered at the firſt appearance of the Kings Standard. <hi>Reez, Emmerick,</hi> and <hi>Groll,</hi> were delivered to the Biſhop of <hi>Munster,</hi> who had taken up Arms to vindicate the <hi>French</hi> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel.</p>
                  <p>The next attempt was, the Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age over the <hi>Rhine,</hi> which was firſt
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:199150:98"/>undertaken by the Count <hi>de Guiche,</hi> at the Head of Two thouſand Horſe, he ſwom over it, although three Squadrons of Horſe, and ſome few Foot, were ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him on the other ſide. When the <hi>French</hi> had recovered the Bank, they charged ſo deſperately, that the Enemy was diſordered, and fled to their Foot for ſuccor. They had Barricadoed themſelves in, but when the Prince, and the Dukes of <hi>Orleans</hi> and <hi>Longueville,</hi> were got on the other ſide with their Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, they reſolved to aſſault them in their Trenches. The Prince de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to march in order againſt them, but ſome of his Men were ſo furious, that nothing could keep them in. The Duke of <hi>Longueville,</hi> in a rage, went ſo near them, with the Prince, that the Duke was kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Prince wounded in the left arm, with many more laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ground.</p>
                  <pb n="193" facs="tcp:199150:98"/>
                  <p>When they ſaw the whole Army ſurround them, they deſired quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which was granted by the Prince, by that means they yielded, and were all taken priſoners. It is not good to render an Enemy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate, a ſmall company in a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger have won the victory; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prince freely offered them their lives.</p>
                  <p>This Action amazed the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander,</hi> and aſtoniſhed the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who expected the Kings Army another way. <hi>Harnen</hi> was taken by Monſieur <hi>de Turenne, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meguen</hi> and <hi>Schenk</hi> alſo. <hi>Does<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourgh</hi> and <hi>Zutphen,</hi> were ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed into his Majeſties hands, and the City of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht</hi> ſent Deputies to yield it up. Monſieur <hi>de Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emburgh</hi> was ſent thither to take in all the places about <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht.</hi> After this, <hi>Turenne</hi> recovered <hi>Crevecoeur, Coërden, Grave,</hi> and <hi>Bomel;</hi> ſo that almoſt all the Inland Countrey
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:199150:99"/>thereabouts, ſubmitted to the <hi>French.</hi> The <hi>Hollanders</hi> were then ſo much troubled, that they offered Conditions of Peace to the King; but he hoped to gain all the reſt of their Countrey: Therefore they were rejected as unreaſonable.</p>
                  <p>The King after all theſe Succeſſes, left the Army the Six and twentieth of <hi>July,</hi> and arrived at <hi>Paris</hi> the firſt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> where he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulated and welcomed by all the Societies of his Kingdom. The Queen was ſo much overjoyed, that ſhe commanded a Chappel to be built at <hi>Roan,</hi> and dedicated it to <hi>Our Lady of Victories;</hi> for as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Heathens they did give to <hi>Pallas,</hi> the Goddeſs of War, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral attributes, and names be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokening the many good Office that they fancied, proceeded fron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> her favoring of them: So the Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſts aſſign divers, and differing ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> who is
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:199150:99"/>now become the Goddeſs of War amongſt them, and the Giver of Victory to her devout Proſelites.</p>
                  <p>The Princes wound had caſt him into an indiſpoſition, which made him follow his Majeſty, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> the Kings Brother, to <hi>Paris,</hi> leaving the Conduct of Affairs to Monſieur <hi>de Luxembourgh</hi> and <hi>Turenne.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was then before <hi>Voërden</hi> with Twelve thouſand Men; <hi>Luxembourgh</hi> prepares a ſtrong brigade of Two thouſand five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Men, and by a ſecret way over the Marſhes, he gets into the Town undiſcovered, with his Party, with which he made ſuch ſtout Sallies, that the Prince was forced to riſe from thence with his Army, to leave ſome of his Baggage and Cannon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him.</p>
                  <p>All this while the <hi>Dutch</hi> had ſcarce time to look about, the <hi>French</hi> had been ſo nimble and
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:199150:100"/>furious, that they had gained all this Countrey, without any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable loſs. But before the next Campagne, the face of affairs was changed, the <hi>Dutch</hi> had many Armies come to their aſſiſtance, the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> the <hi>German,</hi> and the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialists,</hi> ſent their powerful Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors to aid them: So that they have ſince recovered a great part of what they firſt loſt, and will, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all probability, recover the reſt.</p>
                  <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was now reſtored by Order of the States, after the inhumane maſſacre of <hi>de Wit,</hi> to his Patrimonial Offices of <hi>Statholder, Admiral,</hi> and <hi>General of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited-Provinces.</hi> This generous Prince began to appear at the Head of an Army of 24000 Men; with theſe he reſolved not to be idle; ſome places he took, but did not yet dare to adventure againſt his inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Enemy, triumphing for ſo many
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:199150:100"/>great Succeſſes. <hi>Monterey,</hi> Viceroy of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> for the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> deſired him to attempt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in his Countrey, becauſe the <hi>French</hi> had drained their Garriſons; for the <hi>Spaniard</hi> had not declared yet againſt them. According to this advice, he laid ſiege to <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy,</hi> a Fortreſs that was likely to annoy the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> their next Neighbors. <hi>Montal,</hi> the Governor, had notice of the deſign, he Poſts: thither in haſte; and taking his: time in the night, he paſſed through the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Troops, and got ſafe into the Garriſon, to the great joy of the beſieged. The next day he adventured to ſally out with a ſtrong party, which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and welcomed by the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> with loſs on both ſides. When the King heard of this ſiege, he drew near to the Borders of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardy,</hi> and gave order to ſeveral thouſands of his Soldiers to meet
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:199150:101"/>him, with a deſign to beat the <hi>Dutch</hi> off. Therefore this intelligence cauſed the Prince to riſe with his Army, the Two and twentieth day of <hi>December,</hi> and depart: Which was ſignified to the King by a Poſt, ſent from the Governor.</p>
                  <p>At this time, <hi>Luxembourgh</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to lead his Men over the Ice, to Aſſault <hi>Bodengrave, Swam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merdam,</hi> and <hi>Niverburgh;</hi> which three places he took without much reſiſtance. After this, the <hi>French</hi> went no further till the next Spring, 1673. They were all ſent into ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Garriſons, where we ſhall leave them to take notice of their behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or at Sea.</p>
                  <p>On the Water, as well as on the Land, the War was carried on. The <hi>Dutch</hi> had a gallant Fleet, with which they did defie the Fleets of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France:</hi> But though <hi>De Ruyter,</hi> their Admiral, labored by Policy to fight us, and to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:199150:101"/>us at an advantage; he was much miſtaken to find our <hi>Engliſh</hi> courage, in the greateſt diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not to reſiſt and brave Death it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>His Majeſty of <hi>England</hi> had been engaged to joyn his ſtrong Fleet with the <hi>French</hi> Squadron, which was commanded by the Count <hi>de Eſtrées.</hi> Therefore the Twenty eighth of <hi>May,</hi> 1672. in proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the War that had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared againſt the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> our Fleet, under the command of the brave Duke of <hi>York,</hi> had a very ſharp Engagement with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Coaſt; in which, the Victory declared for the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> with the loſs of the <hi>Royal James,</hi> which was unfortunately burned; and of the Earl of <hi>Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> who was drowned, and his body found about the tenth of the next Moneth floating on the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhore. He was an excellent Captain,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:199150:102"/>more fortunate in the <hi>Mediterrane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and in the <hi>Sound,</hi> then in our Channel. <hi>England</hi> lamented the loſs of ſo excellent a perſon. It ſeems his courage deſtroyed him; for when his Ship was Boarded and Fired by a <hi>Dutchman,</hi> when it was ſurrounded by many of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies beſt Ships; His reſolution to brave Death, and the Enemy, in the midſt of the greateſt diſadvantages and dangers, made him abide and continue the ſight in his Flaming Ship.</p>
                  <p>Of our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> Twenty four Perſons of Note were killed, with three of the <hi>French.</hi> Amongſt the reſt, a Gentleman, ſo Courageous, Learned, Civil, and ſo well accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, that I cannot but mention him in this place: It was Mr. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Cotterel,</hi> Sir <hi>Charles Cotterels</hi> Son. About fifteen Gentlemen were deſperately wounded, ſeven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Common Soldiers and Seamen
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:199150:102"/>killed, and as many maimed. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Rabiniere tres le Bois,</hi> Rear Admiral of the <hi>French,</hi> was killed, and buried at <hi>Rochel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Duke of <hi>York,</hi> in this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, behaved himſelf as a diſcreet and wiſe Commander, with an undaunted Courage.</p>
                  <p>It is ſuppoſed, that if our whole Fleet could have had the conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of fighting, the <hi>Dutch</hi> had been for ever undone; but the Wind hindered moſt part of our Ships from coming up to them; ſo that the Blew Squadron was forced to ingage with the Enemy alone. The <hi>Dutch</hi> had great loſs of Men and Ships; it is thought about five or ſix of theirs, beſides the Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips were ſunk: It is certain, that our Fleet purſued them to their own Coaſt.</p>
                  <p>About this time, the Twentieth of <hi>August,</hi> 1672. hapned a moſt barbarous execution of the two
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:199150:103"/>
                     <hi>De Wits</hi> torn in pieces by the rude rabble of the <hi>Hague,</hi> their Privities cut off, their Bodies dragged through the Streets, and hanged at the Gallows, in ſuch a barbarous manner, that the <hi>Cannibals</hi> would have been aſhamed to have done the like.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Groningen</hi> had been beſieged by the Mercenary Weather-cock of <hi>Munſter;</hi> but in the Moneth of <hi>August</hi> he left the Town, after a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable loſs of his Men. The good Biſhop was moved with compaſſion to ſee his Soldiers ſlaughtered by the ſtout-hearted <hi>Dutch;</hi> ſo that he preferred their ſafety, or it may be his own, to the filling of his Purſe with Gilders; which was the thing this noble Captain aimed at in this attempt upon the <hi>Dutch.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The States of <hi>Holland</hi> had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with many of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, eſpecially with the Emperor, King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh,</hi>
                     <pb n="203" facs="tcp:199150:103"/>to ſend their Succors to aſſiſt them by Land. The Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> was perſwaded, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his Alliance with <hi>France,</hi> to enter into the party. They were all reſolved to ſend into the Field their Armies, in the next Spring; for they were afraid that the <hi>French</hi> would not be content with the Conqueſt of <hi>Holland,</hi> but would incroach upon them alſo after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
                  <p>During this Winter, nothing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned worthy of notice, but the loſs of private perſons, robberies, and ſmall Encounters of Parties, that ſought for Plunder and Booties.</p>
                  <p>In the beginning of the Spring, 1673. three Armies appeared for the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> the King of <hi>Spains</hi> commanded by the Count <hi>de Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terey,</hi> the Emperors by <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Brandenburghs</hi> by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; beſides the Army of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who was declared Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:199150:104"/>at Land, Admiral at Sea, and Statholder by the States. The <hi>French</hi> Army commanded by <hi>Turenne,</hi> marched againſt the Duke of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh,</hi> who was forced to quit to him all the County of <hi>Marck,</hi> and to leave his Bag and Baggage behind him, for fear of a total de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat of his Forces. The <hi>French</hi> took <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rnia, Ham, Camen, Altenau, Soeſt,</hi> and <hi>Hoexter, Bilefeld,</hi> and <hi>Ravenſperg,</hi> ſmall places of no ſtrength.</p>
                  <p>At this time, the <hi>Swede</hi> and the <hi>Dane,</hi> with other Neuter Princes, had deſired an accommodation of the differences between the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France. Cologne</hi> was the place of meeting; all the Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ipotentiaries were ſent with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions: But although the <hi>Dutch</hi> had ſo many loſſes by Land, and by Sea, they would not yield to any reaſonable Propoſitions at firſt. Their ſtout hearts were reſolved to
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:199150:104"/>try the Fortune of War, before they would liſten to any peaceable concluſion. At laſt after ſeveral De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, and Conſultations, the Peace was concluded between the King of <hi>England</hi> and the States, but the <hi>French</hi> pretentions were extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary high, and their Succeſſes great; ſo that there was no poſſibility that did appear, to end their differences at this time. But before the Peace was publiſhed between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> all this Summer of the year 1673. the War was vigorouſly carried on by Sea and Land.</p>
                  <p>By Sea, Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Fleet of <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> One hundred and twenty Sail. With theſe Ships he attacked the <hi>Dutch</hi> Frigats, under the command of <hi>De Ruyter</hi> and <hi>Van Trump.</hi> The fight was mannaged with much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution on both ſides: The <hi>French</hi> in the former Engagements had been taught to face their Enemy
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:199150:105"/>upon the Water; for they behaved themſelves now very bravely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they could not well excuſe themſelves. It is certain, the Princes conduct and courage in this, and all other Engagements, have juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the praiſe of all Men, and the thanks of our Nation. This noble Spirit hath ſince his infancy, ſpent his Wit and Blood in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and for the honor of our Countrey.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> proclaimed Victory at Land, whileſt their Ships and Shipwracks complained of their ill uſage at Sea by the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> They loſt eight conſiderable Veſſels, that of <hi>Van Haen</hi> was the chief, it was blown up by an unfortunate ſhot. Many were ſo diſabled, that they could not reach into their Harbors. His Majeſties Fleet had received ſome damage in the Rigging, and loſs of Men; but not ſo as to hinder them the next morning, the nineth
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:199150:105"/>of <hi>May,</hi> from purſuing their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to their own Coaſt. The <hi>Dutch</hi> loſt many Men, ſome of note, and a Ship taken by the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At Land there were frequent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters between the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French.</hi> The City of <hi>Maſtreicht</hi> was the cheif place of action this Summer: The Count <hi>de Lorge,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Montall,</hi> were ordered to inveſt it, the ſixth of <hi>June:</hi> The reſt of the Army marched thither to poſt themſelves about this ſtrong place. <hi>Fario</hi> was then Governor, with a very ſtout Garriſon of ſix thouſand Men; the Count <hi>de Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terey</hi> had ſent thither two thouſand <hi>Italian</hi> Horſe and Foot, to reinforce the place. The King himſelf was in the Army with the braveſt and choiceſt Regiments; and the Noble Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> with ſeveral thouſand <hi>Engliſh</hi> under his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
                  <pb n="208" facs="tcp:199150:106"/>
                  <p>It is certain, the <hi>French</hi> King viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Trenches, and incouraged his Troops, with a great contempt of the danger. <hi>Fario</hi> had ſent him this civil meſſage, That if he knew whereabouts his Majeſties Quarters were, he would command his Men to forbear ſhooting to that place: The King ſent him word again, That his Quarters were every where in his Camp. The beſieged made a ſtout reſiſtance, many Men were kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on both ſides. It is thought that this Town might have put a ſtop to the <hi>French</hi> Conqueſts, if the Burgers had been more faithful to their old Maſters, and leſs careleſs of their lives and riches. It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that it had never been taken by the <hi>French</hi> alone, had not our <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſpent their blood, and in contempt of all danger, paſſed with their Regiments through ſhowers of ſmall and great ſhot, to the Aſſault.</p>
                  <pb n="209" facs="tcp:199150:106"/>
                  <p>We cannot ſufficiently admire the courage of the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> a young General of an admirable conduct and skill in Martial Affairs. He commanded in the Trenches, with an intention to aſſault the Counterſcarpe, and the Half-Moon, before <hi>Bruſſels-Gate.</hi> He led on his Men with ſuch reſolution, that though two or three Mines were ſprung up, and the ſhot fell thick amongſt them, they carried the Half-Moon, to the great wonder of all men, in half an hour.</p>
                  <p>As ſoon as it was taken, the Duke, with his Party, was immediately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved by the <hi>French,</hi> upon whom, the beſieged played ſo briskly, with their great and ſmall ſhot, that they beat them out with the aſſiſtance of a Mine, and a ſtout Sally. When the Duke ſaw that the <hi>French</hi> had loſt what his Men had got, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared himſelf to regain it; which he did with the greateſt reſolution
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:199150:107"/>and happineſs imaginable. This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible ſpirit at the Head of his Party, leaped over the Trenches firſt, with his Weapon in his hand, only twelve ſtout Voluntiers accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied him, the reſt followed ſo furiouſly, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> were beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en off again, and his Grace became Maſter of the Half-Moon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time, delivering it into the hands of Monſieur <hi>de la Feuillade.</hi> So that without flattery, the <hi>French</hi> ow the taking of <hi>Maſtreicht</hi> to the courage, conduct, and brave reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> to the Blood and undauntedneſs of our <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Jones</hi> was killed in one of theſe aſſaults, which hapned the twenty fourth of <hi>June.</hi> After ſome other attempts, where our Men were again imployed, the Town deſired a Parley the twenty nineth, and in two hours the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles were granted, That the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor and Garriſon ſhould march
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:199150:107"/>out as ſtout Soldiers, their Colours flying, Drums beating, Match light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Bullet in Mouth, with Bag and Baggage, and two Pieces of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, and a Mortar Piece. That they ſhould be ſafely convoyed to <hi>Boiſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due</hi> and <hi>Breda.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> loſt 4000 Men, and about 1000 of the beſieged were killed. The King took poſſeſſion of it the thirtieth of <hi>June,</hi> and commanded the Cardinal <hi>de Boüillon</hi> to reſanctifie the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es profaned by the <hi>Dutches</hi> Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                  <p>About this time there hapned an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Sea-ſight, between the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleets, with loſs on both ſides; but our <hi>Engliſh</hi> beat the boaſting <hi>Dutch</hi> again into their Harbors, where they left them to complain of their wounds and dead, and to glory in their pretended Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes and Victories.</p>
                  <p>The many Armies that were now on foot, to attend upon and ſtop
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:199150:108"/>the further proceedings of the <hi>French,</hi> cauſed them to call away their Garriſons from many Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Towns: Beſides the Sickneſs and the War, had conſumed a great number; ſo that they were forced, for their own ſafety, to gather a little more cloſe together. Several ſtrong places were abandoned, and ſeveral were diſmantled; the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers were ſent to reinforce the Armies.</p>
                  <p>During this Winter, many En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters hapned between the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and ſome few unconſiderable places taken. But now to the great joy of <hi>England,</hi> it pleaſed His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to grant a Peace to the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander,</hi> on moſt honorable Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>French</hi> King nevertheleſs continues his deſigns by Land; but by Sea he commands his Ships to be drawn up, or to ſail out of the Dutchmens ſight. In the beginning
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:199150:108"/>of the Spring he beſieged <hi>Beſanzon,</hi> in the <hi>Franche Comté; Peſme, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay,</hi> were taken before by the Duke of <hi>Navailles,</hi> the fourteenth of <hi>February.</hi> The ſtrong Town of <hi>Gray</hi> was yielded up after two or three days ſiege: On the twenty eighth, <hi>Veſoal</hi> was alſo taken. The King himſelf, with a ſtrong Party, arrived at his Camp before <hi>Beſanzon,</hi> in the beginning of <hi>May,</hi> 1674. It was ſurrendered into his Majeſties hands before the end of the Moneth, after many brave exploits and much blood ſhed.</p>
                  <p>Whiles the Treaty was on foot at <hi>Cologne,</hi> the Emperor cauſed the Prince of <hi>Furſtemberg,</hi> Plenipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiary for the Archbiſhop of <hi>Cologne,</hi> to be arreſted by the Officers of his Regiment of <hi>Grana,</hi> in his Coach, and carried to <hi>Bon,</hi> becauſe he had not maintained the intereſt of the Empire, as he ſhould have done, he being a Subject.</p>
                  <pb n="214" facs="tcp:199150:109"/>
                  <p>This violent proceeding did mightily ſcandaliſe all the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors, eſpecially the Archbiſhop, and the <hi>French</hi> King, were offended at this violence: For they pretend, that the perſon of an Ambaſſador is ſacred, and not to be violated by any means. <hi>Nature</hi> hath taught the moſt barbarous people to ſuffer them to go and come in ſafety, who are imployed in quenching the Flames of War.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Navaigne</hi> was afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged and yielded to the Prince of <hi>Condé;</hi> but the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> had an intent to ſuccor it, had not the beſieged made ſo much haſte to ſecure their lives by a Surrender. <hi>Dole</hi> was alſo beſieged by the King, and taken after a ſtout reſiſtance.</p>
                  <p>The fifteenth of <hi>June,</hi> there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a fight between Monſieur <hi>de Turenne,</hi> and the Imperialiſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> and the Count of <hi>Caprara.</hi> The
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:199150:109"/>Duke of <hi>Bournonville</hi> was march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to them, <hi>Turenne</hi> reſolved to hinder a conjunction; for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he paſſed the <hi>Rhine</hi> at <hi>Philips<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh.</hi> The Duke and Count had but Seven thouſand Horſe, and a Regiment of Foot, but <hi>Turenne</hi> was Twelve thouſand ſtrong. The Confederates behaved themſelves ſo bravely, that had they not been inferior in number, they had forced the <hi>French</hi> to a retreat. After a hot ingagement, which laſted all the Afternoon, the <hi>Germans</hi> ſought their fafety in a retreat over the <hi>Neckar;</hi> many brave Men were kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on both ſides, ſome ſay the loſs was equal. It is certain, four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men lay dead on the Ground; the old Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> headed his Troops with ſo much reſolution, as if he had intended to win a Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in another World, by his not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able courage.</p>
                  <pb n="216" facs="tcp:199150:110"/>
                  <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet, about one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Sail, paſſed out of the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel to ſcoure the Seas, of all <hi>French</hi> Frigats, and to attempt ſomething upon the Coaſt; they Landed on <hi>Belle Iſle,</hi> but were repulſed after the loſs of a few Men.</p>
                  <p>The Duke of <hi>Schomberg</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the <hi>French</hi> Forces in <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia;</hi> in the County of <hi>Rouſillon,</hi> he ingaged with them, and forced them to a retreat, with the loſs of his Son, and another Gentleman of quality taken priſoners.</p>
                  <p>The next action was between the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> aſſiſted by the Count <hi>de Souches,</hi> the eleventh of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> near <hi>Haynault.</hi> The two Armies were reſolved to have a bruſh, which was performed with much gallantry: The Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> Army loſt many Men, and Commanders; and the <hi>French</hi> diſputed the caſe very ſtoutly; at laſt they retreated into
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:199150:110"/>their Camp, carrying with them many noble priſoners, and moſt part of the Princes Baggage; leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Dutch</hi> to boaſt of their empty and ſorrowful Victory, in the open Field.</p>
                  <p>At this time <hi>Grave</hi> was beſieged by the <hi>Dutch:</hi> The <hi>French</hi> could not be perſwaded to ſurrender it, till after a long and bloody ſiege.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Meſſinenſes</hi> had revolted from the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the <hi>French</hi> protection. The Duke <hi>de Vivonne</hi> arrived there, with ſome Succors, and relief of Men, and Proviſion. The Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants put them in poſſeſſion of the ſtrongeſt places about the City; the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> by Sea and Land, endeavored to plague them. A ſhort conflict hapned upon the Coaſt, between the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleets, where the noiſe of their great Guns, and their mutual Rodomontadoes, ſoon terrified
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:199150:111"/>them, and made them both willing to part upon equal terms. By this means the <hi>Meſſinenſes</hi> had ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion brought to them in their ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent neceſſity.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>October,</hi> the Confederates, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped upon the skirts of <hi>Turennes</hi> Army, were forced to fight near <hi>Strasburgh;</hi> they loſt three thouſand Men, ten Pieces of Cannon, thirty Standards, and many Priſoners; the <hi>French</hi> alſo had many of their beſt Menkilled. The Confederates re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to <hi>Spire,</hi> and <hi>Turenne</hi> to the ſides of the <hi>Rhine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The taking of the Cittadel of <hi>Leige</hi> this Winter, by the <hi>French,</hi> was an accident, that ſurpriſed and ſtartled all the World. It was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed by a treacherous Governor, and delivered into the Kings hands, who ſent thither three thouſand Men to remain in Garriſon.</p>
                  <p>This year 1675 the War con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues ſtill call <hi>Europe</hi> is ingaged in
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:199150:111"/>this Bloody diſpute, between the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch.</hi> The <hi>Swedes</hi> have been perſwaded, for the <hi>French</hi> ſake to enter into the Borders of the Duke of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and in defence of the Proteſtant Intereſt, as they pretend, to help the <hi>French,</hi> who carries on the Popes. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have quartered their Army all this Winter, upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> who hath been forced to draw his Army from the Confederates to ſtop the <hi>Swedes</hi> violences.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>May</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King cauſed <hi>Limburgh</hi> to be beſieged, after the taking of <hi>Huy</hi> and <hi>Dinant.</hi> The Confederates were reſolved to raiſe the ſiege, but the ſurrender pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented them. Nevertheleſs the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> have behaved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves very ſtoutly in the defence of this Town.</p>
                  <p>At preſent the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> with his Army, attends upon the
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:199150:112"/>
                     <hi>French</hi> King near <hi>Ruremond; Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renne</hi> is incamped near the <hi>Rhine,</hi> about <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> in ſight of the <hi>German,</hi> commanded by <hi>Montecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi.</hi> All the World expects to hear of a bloody diſpute between them. What end this great quarrel will have, God alone knows; however we ought to lament at the miſeries of our Neighbors, at the Chriſtian Blood that is ſhed to ſatisfie the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of a Prince that wants no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on Earth, but Content. We ought to pray God to preſerve our <hi>England,</hi> in Peace and Unity; and our gracious King, the beſt of all Monarchs, in health and proſperity.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:199150:112"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
